<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons The first preached at St Maries in Oxford Iuly 13. 1634. being Act-Sunday. The second, in the cathedrall church of Sarum, at the visitation of the most Reverend Father in God William Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, May 23. 1634. By Thomas Laurence Dr of Divinity, and late Fellow of Allsoules Colledge, and chaplaine to his Maiesty in ordinary.</title>
            <author>Laurence, Thomas, 1598-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108386</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05193)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 805:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons The first preached at St Maries in Oxford Iuly 13. 1634. being Act-Sunday. The second, in the cathedrall church of Sarum, at the visitation of the most Reverend Father in God William Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, May 23. 1634. By Thomas Laurence Dr of Divinity, and late Fellow of Allsoules Colledge, and chaplaine to his Maiesty in ordinary.</title>
                  <author>Laurence, Thomas, 1598-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40; 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: [A]²  a-e⁴ A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>"Of schismes in the Church of God" (running title) has separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS THE FIRST PREACHED AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>MARIES</hi> in OXFORD Iuly 13. 1634. being Act-Sunday. THE SECOND, IN THE CATHEDRALL CHVRCH OF <hi>SARVM,</hi> AT THE Viſitation of the moſt Reverend Father in God WILLIAM Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, May</hi> 23. 1634.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS LAVRENCE D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Divinity, and late Fellow of <hi>Allſoules</hi> Colledge, and Chaplaine to his MAIESTY <hi>in</hi> ORDINARY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8829:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8829:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EXOD. 20.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the people ſtood a farre off, and Moſes drew neere vnto the thicke darkneſſe, where God was.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD made man, placed him in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſpake to him, in the ſecond of Geneſis, and man was not afraide. God came in a <hi>walking voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Votem itan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Iun. &amp; Trem.</note> in the third of Geneſis, and man was afraid: becauſe he had not ſinned in the ſecond chapter, and had ſinned in the third. For where no ſinne is, there is no feare: <hi>perfect loue,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iohn, caſteth out feare,</hi> which therefore is not fit company for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe loue is perfect there. The happineſſe of that place conſiſts in the viſion of God, <hi>in whoſe preſence is the fulneſse of ioy,</hi> ſaith <hi>David:</hi> which therefore <hi>the ſoules vnder the Altar,</hi> as S. Iohn; or <hi>in their chambers,</hi> as <hi>Eſdras</hi> ſpeakes, long to ſee,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8829:3"/>
ſaying, <hi>when cometh the fruit of our reward?</hi> in the ſecond of that ſtory, the fourth chapter, at the fiue and thirtieth verſe? And who deſires what hee trembles at, or joyes in that hee feares? But tis otherwiſe here. In Heaven wee ſhall bee raviſhed with God, not afraid of him; in earth, wee are afraid of any meſſenger from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. An Angell appeared to<note n="b" place="margin">Iud. 6.22.</note> 
               <hi>Gedeon,</hi> and hee was afraid; an Angell appeared to<note n="c" place="margin">C. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>Manoah,</hi> and he was afraid; an Angell appeared to the<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 2.10.</note> Sheapheards, &amp; theſe were afraid; an Angell appeared to the<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and they were afraid. Afraid all of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, which brought the meſſage of joy. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ever ſince an Angell guarded Paradice with a drawn ſword, we haue deſerved no good news from aboue, we conceiue no other deſigne of ſuch Meſſengers, but to ſtrike. And what ſhall Iſrael feare from God himſelfe, if theſe imagined no leſſe then death from the ſight of an Angell? That glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious juſt Lord, cannot beſpeake my damnable vileneſſe but in thunder; and therefore, if <hi>Moſes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they ſhall liue to keepe the Law, <hi>Moſes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe muſt deliver the Law: God muſt ſpeake no more <hi>leaſt they dye,</hi> v. 19 He comforted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed, and ſaid <hi>feare not,</hi> v. 20. which is all one, as if hee ſhould ſay, ſinne not: for while they were guilty of ſinne, they muſt be ſubiect to feare. Bounds were defined, vnto which they came not, and yet they came too neere. Gods command remoues them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8829:3"/>
farre, and their owne feare remoues them farther; <hi>And the people stood a farre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words repreſent the duty of the Laity in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael the people, and the priviledge of the Clergy in <hi>Moſes</hi> their Prieſt. So the holy Ghoſt eſteemed him <hi>Moſes and Aron among the Prieſts, Pſal.</hi> 99.6. ſo thoſe Apoſtolicall conſtitutions eſteemed him,<note place="margin">L. 6. c. 3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, L. 2. c. 29. ſo hee eſteemed himſelfe; ſanctifying the aſſembly,<note place="margin">Exod. 19.14.</note> dedicating the Tabernacles, hallowing the veſſells, offering ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, conſecrating <hi>Aron</hi> with his Sonnes, and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating both for the Scepter and the Mitre too, the Prince and the Prieſt; to ſhew that there is no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall repugnancie, betwixt the Ephod and the Maze, the Tribunall and the Altar, but that both thriue the better for the vicinity of each other, as the Vine helpes the Elme, and by this neighbourhood climbes the higher.</p>
            <p>The duty of the Laity requires,
<list>
                  <item>1 An obſequious attention to God; <hi>the people ſtood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 An humble diſtance from God; <hi>The people ſtood a farre off.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The priviledge of the Clergy diſcovers,
<list>
                  <item>1 The approximation, or immediatneſſe of their acceſſe, <hi>Moſes drew neere.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The limitation of this approximation; <hi>Moſes drew neere vnto the thicke darkneſse.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The condition of this limitation, <hi>Moſes drew
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8829:4"/>
neere vnto the thicke darkneſſe, where God was.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Vox vagina ſenſus,</hi> Language is the ſheath of ſenſe,<note place="margin">Bel. de not. Ecc. l. 4. c. 12.</note> ſaith the Cardinall; and words are the attire of the minde, ſaith the Oratour, he therefore (whoſe tongue is too big for his heart, that ſpeakes more then he thinkes) caſes a needle in a ſcabberd, and preſents little David in great Goliahs armour, or rather araies a child with the clothes of a gyant, and ſo inveſts him not with a ſuit but enſtates in a houſe. God is no friend to the hypocriſy of complement, and therefore in Scripture ever meanes more then he ſpeakes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>the words of the Lord are pure words, as ſilver tried ſeaven times in the fire,</hi> ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, calcined and ſublimated from this droſse: for he is a God of truths, not of varniſhes; of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities not of ſhadowes. He hates that mouth which belies the minde, and likes men on earth beſt, when they reſemble, the Saints in Heaven; where ſoules commerce <hi>per verbum mentis,</hi> without tongues; and thoughts are ſeene without the mediation of words; tis ſo in my Text, where a ſyllable of Gods ſignifies more then a volume of mans; a word of His then a Library of mine; and the peoples ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here comprehends as much as the people ſhould doe, and much more indeede then they would.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſtanding is a poſture of reſpect; wee kneele and ſtand to our ſuperiours: Kneele to ſhew our ſubiection, and ſtand to ſhew our obedience: that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8829:4"/>
we are ready to execute, what theſe are to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Seeſt thou a man diligent in his buſineſse, hee ſhall ſtand before Kings,</hi> Prov. 22.29. and although <hi>the Angells turned their faces to Sodome, Abraham ſtood yet before the Lord,</hi> Gen. 18.22. Standing and Kneeling then become inferiours, ſitting doth not, <hi>the Lord ſaid to my Lord, ſit thou at my right hand:</hi> ther's an equality of nature betwixt the Father and the Sonne, and therefore one ſits by the other, Pſal. 110.11. and <hi>when the ſonne of man ſhall ſit on the Throne of his glory, then ſhall yee alſo ſit vpon twelue Thrones, Iudging the twelue Tribes of Iſrael:</hi> there's an equality of grace or favour, betwixt the Iudge and his Aſſeſſors, &amp; therefore theſe haue Thrones together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.18. ſo that thoſe Antipodes which tread croſſe to the World, which faſt at the birth of our Saviour, and feaſt at his paſſion, which will not ſay Chriſtmas, and yet will call a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Demas, which ſit at the Altar, becauſe we kneele; ſay not with the Syrophaenician, <hi>Lord</hi> I <hi>am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eate the crummes vnder thy table;</hi> but Lord I am worthy to ſit at thy table, I am as good as thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Standing then is a poſture of reſpect, and reſpect is, a preparatiue to attention, for no man liſtens to what he ſcornes. <hi>Lydias</hi> affection muſt be warmed, before ſhe can attend; regard S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhee muſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe can heare him; <hi>when God ſhall open her heart,</hi> then will ſhe open her eares, Act. 16.14. nor won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8829:5"/>
I, the converſions of this Apoſtle were ſo many, ſeeing his honours were ſo great;<note place="margin">Veni, vidi, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci.</note> like that Romane commander he conquered as many Nations as hee ſaw, whereſoever he came, his Saviour followed him: and therefore his ſtay was not ſo long any where, his travailes more frequent and farther then thoſe of others: <hi>in labours more abundant he was, and in iourneying often,</hi> 2. Cor. 11.23.26. For God bleſt him with ſuch as would pull out their owne eyes in his behalfe: their owne eyes, not his ſuch as had humility enough to learne, had not pride e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to teach the Apoſtle: ſuch as believed his eyes ſo much, that they thought they had no vſe of their owne, Galat. 4.15. <hi>heare therefore the word of the Lord, yee that tremble at his word,</hi> Eſa. 66.3. as if none were fit to heare but ſuch, the reſt not worth the looking after, as indeede they are not: for <hi>to him will</hi> I <hi>looke that trembleth at my word:</hi> ſuch I will looke after, and I will not looke after thoſe, that are not ſuch; in the ſecond verſe of that chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 Paral. 6.3.</note>2 Standing is a poſture of attention, the poſture of hearers; <hi>when Ezra opened the Law, all the people ſtood vp,</hi> Nehem. 8.5. there is no duty oftner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned then this: Foure times in two chapters, the ſecond and the third of the Apocalypſe; nay foure times in one chapter, the fiue and fiftieth of Eſaiah: more, three times in one line, <hi>giue eare, and come vnto mee, hearken, and your ſoule ſhall liue.</hi> Heauen
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8829:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is the reward of your attention, hell of your ſcorne, in the third verſe of that chapter: <hi>behold I stand at the doore and knocke, if any man heare my voice, and open the doore,</hi> I <hi>will come in:</hi> behold, becauſe hee knocks not often, for hee that ſtands is going away: eſpecially if he ſtand at the doore without a ſhelter; if he ſtand only to knocke, and not to knocke nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after he is ſleighted; this were to awake the deafe, or ſpeake to the dumbe, Apocal. 3.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Lord, who hath believed our report, or to whom hath the arme of the Lord beene revealed?</hi> Where are thoſe throngs now, and preſſes vpon Chriſt? Where is that early comming in the Goſpell? how ſoone are wee vp to ſport, and how late to pray?<note place="margin">Luke. 21.38. Io. 8.2.</note> how ſmall in many places, is the gleaning of their Churches to the vintage of their Citties? how low is the ebbe in thoſe courts of the Lord, when tis full ſea in their Streets?<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.17.</note> how doe we <hi>looke the Prieſt in the face, and cast his words behind our backs,</hi> as David complaines? his ordinary entertainement reſembling that of Muſique,<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.32.</note> which ſerues only to fill our eares, when diſcourſe is done. Good women there were, which conſecrated their looking glaſſes to the tabernacle, Exod. 38.8. and will yee know, how ye may doe ſo now? By vſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bible on the Sunday, and comming hither with halfe a dreſſe, then loſing halfe a prayer. Wherefore <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera ab homine malo,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> that is <hi>à meipſo</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi> deliver me from my ſelfe ô God, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8829:6"/>
I may come hither, and from my ſelfe, while I am here; from my covetous ſelfe, leaſt the thought of my purchaſe ſhut out my Lord; &amp; from my proud ſelfe, when he honours, or worſhips me; from my malitious ſelfe, when an injury heates my bloud; and from my wanton ſelfe, when the aſſembly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſes a beauty, a well attired piece of hanſome clay; from my intemperate ſelfe, when the thought of Aegypt brings on mee a lothing of Canaan; and from my prophane ſelfe, when ſome incarnate Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan aſſailes my attention, by whiſpering in his vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at my eares, and clothing his Atheiſme with the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Standing is a poſture of action, the poſture of ſervants: <hi>GehaZi went in, and ſtood before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> the readier therefore to come, or goe at his command, 2. Reg. 5.25. Practice is the life of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he that heares, but does not, is a monſter in religion, that hath two eares, and no hands. The Iews were taught this by their meates, and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall law was but a ſhadow of the Morall. What poyſonous temper in the hare? What dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous nouriſhment in the ſwine? Why might they not as freely feede on the rabbet, as the ſheepe? Or what Philoſophy makes the goate more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome then the crab or the ſwan? <hi>he ſhewed by this, O man, what is good, and what the Lord requires of thee:</hi> thy effeminateneſſe is forbidden in the hare; which changeth his ſexe, as <hi>Geſner</hi> writes, and is,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8829:6"/>
at ſeverall times, both hee and ſhee: and thy lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the downe of the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit. 11.18 Deut. 14.16.</hi> Cygnum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Vulg. Sept Vatabl. Ariam. Mont. Anglican. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimam: alij aliter reddunt vt Tremel. Leo Iudas, Munſter, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal.</note> Swan. Thy oppreſſion is interdicted in the Eagle, and thy drunkenneſſe in the Swine. Thy gluttons prey on Cormorants, and thy night-walkers on owles: for God inſtructed them what they ſhould doe, by what they might eate, and every prohibited meate was a menace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne; Or leaſt this light ſhould ſeeme too dimme, he deſcribes the ſame with the raies of the Sunne: <hi>hee that lifteth not his eyes to idolls, defileth not his neighbours wife, ſpoileth none by violence, giues not vpon vſury, reſtoreth the pledge, beſtowes his bread on the hungry, walketh in my ſtatutes, hee ſhall ſurely liue:</hi> he is not juſt that hath faith, vnleſſe he haue workes too, nor doth the Goſpell ſaue without the law, Ezek. 18.6.7.8. 'tis S. <hi>Aug:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cont. Fauſt. l. 22. c. 24.</note> ſpeech of the ancient Prophets, <hi>illorum non tantum lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam, ſed vitam fuiſſe Propheticam:</hi> that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied as well by their liues as their writings, and their ſixe daies contain'd a commentary on the ſeaventh. For if I cry <hi>the Temple of the Lord,</hi> but obey not the Lord of the Temple, and am like that Idoll in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that had his head of gold, and his feete of clay; If I runne vpon a precipice, while my eyes are open, and the light of my profeſſion ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me not to keepe mee vp, but to ſhew how dangerous I fell; if I am only Sermon-ſicke, while I am rockt in a Church-tempeſt abroad, and preſently recouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as ſoone as Hye at hull at home; If <hi>my voice
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8829:7"/>
be Iacobs,</hi> but <hi>my hands Eſau's,</hi> and I weare Elias mantle without his ſpirit; if I acknowledge God with my tongue, but deny him in my life, profeſſe a Chriſtian, and liue a Pagan, goe from Church to a brothelhouſe, joyne the ſpirit of Chaſtity and the ſpirit of whoredomes together, the holy, and vnholy Ghoſt, Chriſt and Belial, <hi>the Temple of God, and the Temple of Divells;</hi> if I runne to Heauen one day, to hell ſixe, and contradict the truth of my Sermons by the errour of my life, what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaid to <hi>Amaziah,</hi> the Prieſt may ſay to mee: <hi>I know that the Lord hath determined to destroy thee, becauſe thou haſt done this thing, and hast not heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to my counſell,</hi> 2. Chron. 25.16.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, <hi>when the Sonne of man ſhall come, will he find faith on earth,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, Luc. 18.8?<note place="margin">C. <hi>2.18.</hi> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam diſcipuli cuiuſdam Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marici nomine ſtudentes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifiis dixerunt quod illud quod alias eſt peccatum mortale, vt ſtuprum, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate non eſt peccatum con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demnati &amp; combuſti: ad ſin. Lomb. c. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> yes: faith enough, but no workes. Faith that remoues mountaines, that pulls downe Churches, and clothes not the poore: faith that hates Idolls, and loues Sacriledge, a tunne of faith for a dramme of charity, <hi>ſhew me thy faith by thy workes,</hi> ſaith S. Iames, not ſo, my workes muſt be judged by my faith: <hi>to the pure all things are pure;</hi> and if God ſee my faith, he is not angry with my ſinnes; my tree muſt be eſteemed by the leaues, not by the fruit; and my watch muſt rule the Sunne: heretiques there were, ſtiled by the Church <hi>praedeſtinati,</hi> which preſumed vpon a fatallity of their election, and would needs haue Heauen promiſed, without the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8829:7"/>
condition of workes: for they dreamt of a convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance without a proviſo, and thought themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to aſcend Iacobs Ladder, without climbing by the rounds. But ſuch as make themſelues of Gods counſell, are vſually none of his friends: hee will profeſſe himſelfe a ſtranger to theſe intruders, and a friend to thoſe which obſerved their diſtance: to thoſe that ſaid <hi>we haue eaten with thee, I know you not:</hi> but ſuch as ſaid, <hi>when ſaw wee thee hungry, and fed thee, or thirſty, and gaue thee drinke? Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit a Kingdome;</hi> theſe which pretended leaſt acquaintance, were thoſe onely which obſerved him, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.34. <hi>where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this World,</hi> 1. Cor. 1.20.? ſurely neither in Heauen, nor here. The feare of God was amongſt theſe, this feare wrought reſpect; this reſpect atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this attention obedience: and all this, becauſe they more obſerved what God ſaid, then ſearched what he was: they were neere enough to receiue his command, but not neere enough to pry into his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: neere enough to obey, but not neere enough to ſee him. God commanded them <hi>to ſtand off,</hi> and therefore <hi>they ſtood a farre off;</hi> their humble di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from God, and my ſecond generall.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God was vnwilling the people ſhould forget themſelues, and therefore ſhadowed forth this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo often, in Paradice; by permitting <hi>Adam,</hi> the tree of life, and interdicting the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8829:8"/>
to ſhew hee rather deſires to make vs Saints, then Rabbies, or Doctors. In the wilderneſſe, <hi>Moſes</hi> was hardly permitted a glimpſe, or dawning of his glory, &amp; what red ſea haſt thou diuided, what Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes haſt thou fed from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or water'd out of a rocke, that thou ſhouldſte looke as high as he? At the giuing of the law, that King-prieſt only entred the clouds, <hi>Aron</hi> came almoſt to it; the Elders far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of; and at a remoter ſite the people: Limits are defined, and if they tranſgreſſe theſe; if they <hi>breake through to gaze on God, they muſt die,</hi> in the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of this ſtory, at the one and twentieth verſe. In the ſeruice of the Tabernacle, who were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant but the Leuites? who carried, who kept, who couered, who vncouered but theſe? in the diſpoſall of the Tabernacle, the Laity had a diſtinct court from the Prieſts, as anciently in the Church, the chancell as appropriated to the Clergy; the reſt to the people.<note place="margin">Hence <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio Laica,</hi> from the place, <hi>vid. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomen. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>Theodoret. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 16.17. 1. Reg. 6.31.33.</note> In the building of the temple, the doore into the oracle, was but a fifth part of the wall, in the Kings, that into the <hi>Sanctum</hi> a fourth; to ſhew, that more come into the Church, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arohe many tread the Courts of the Lord, that were never admitted to his counſell. In the waters of the Sanctuary, that roſe to the ankles for the people, and when they were ſwollen aboue the loynes, became too deepe for the Prieſts. In the law, communicated to all; the <hi>Cabala,</hi> as the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies ſay, or traditionall expoſition, from God to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8829:8"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> onely, and from <hi>Moſes</hi> onely to the ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for although Mirandula tell vs,<note place="margin">Apology for his 900 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</note> that Sixtus the fourth procured the tranſlation of this, and call God to witneſſe, that he read there the Miſteryes of our faith, as clearely vnfolded, as if S. Matthew, or S. Luke had deliuered it, not as a paraphraſe on the law, but a commentary on the Goſpell: yet we know, from <hi>Eſdras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Eſd. 14.45.46.</note> what a concealement this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bala was vnder what Hierogliphicks the Trinity, and the reſurrection, and the life, to come; and the <hi>Meſsiah</hi> lay buried vnder the law: how generall and implicite the faith of S. Peter, and <hi>Martha,</hi> and the Eunuch, and thoſe worthies to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> was: which occaſioned that heſitancy at <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.16.17. Io. 11.27. Act. 8.37. c. 11. Act. 19. Act. 15.21.20. Mar. 6.11.13. c. 9.10. c. 8.31.32. Luc. 24.11. c. 9.44.45. Ioh. 10.9. Mat. 16.10.17.22.</note> concerning the reality of the Holy Ghoſt: that conſiſtency for a time of the law, and the Goſpell together, <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt: that irreſolution of the Apoſtles, about the paſſion, and the reſurrection, and the aſcention of our Lord: that deſigne of all vpon the externall glory of a temporall Dominion, admitting no Soueraignty of God, vnles he change his croſſe into a throne, his reede into a ſcepter. In the glory of our Sauiour on the mount, where <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> attended him: in his bloudy ſweate in the garden, where an Angell comforted him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ken of the multitude, with the priuity only of <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> In their diet, <hi>Milke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.2. 1. Pet. 2.2. Ioh. 21.15.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>and not meate,</hi> eaſy poſitiue divinity: in their appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <hi>lambes and ſheepe;</hi> the in apprehenſiueſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8829:9"/>
of any: <hi>Children and Babes,</hi> which moue not a foote, but by the direction of a hand; and ſooner cry for what offends, then what profits them; for poyſon, then an Antidote. In the eſſentiall meaſure of faith:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.9. Ioh. 17.3.</note> no larger then a verſe in <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Creede: <hi>if thou confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and belieue with thy heart, that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt bee ſaved:</hi> no larger then a verſe in <hi rend="sup">t</hi> S. Iohns;<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.13.2. c. 5.15.</note> this is life eternall, that they might know thee, the only true God, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt: nor much larger in that of all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, being dilated thus in that<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Catech. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiphan. in exp. fid. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. n. 19. ed. Petau. regula fidei. Aug. ſer. 181. de temp. clauis caeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amb. Ser. 38. de Ieiun. &amp; quadrag. ſin.</note> foundation of faith, as Cyrill of Ieruſalem, Epiphanius, and S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> call it; <hi>in futurae praedicationis normam,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi> as the compaſſe and ſquare of their Sermons, that all might beate thoſe paths to Heaven eaſier, by tracing the ſame ſteps; and teach but one, though they went ſeverall waies: for the Apoſtles is but an expoſition of S. <hi>Pauls;</hi> and S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Creed, the <hi>Nicene,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> but a paraphraſe on this, ſaith<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Catech. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiphan. in exp. fid. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. n. 19. ed. Petau. regula fidei. Aug. ſer. 181. de temp. clauis caeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amb. Ser. 38. de Ieiun. &amp; quadrag. ſin.</note> 
               <hi>AZor:</hi> the ſame faith in weight, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though not in bulke or ſize: as 'tis the ſame piece in a bullet and a ſheete of gold; that being throng'd into a mould, which beaten and expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by an Artificer, may anon cover and gild all the leaues of my Bible.</p>
            <p>But ô the vnnaturall Chimiſtry of this age! how infinite are the extractions from this ſimple, this ſingle breviary? What ſeas are derived from this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8829:9"/>
drop? Into how generall a flame haue thoſe fiery breathes blowne this ſparke? How ſoone hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vapour, when once it came to a hand, like that in the Kings, raged into a cloud, and this cloud grown too big for Heaven? How haue ſome reſolved all the hereſies S. <hi>Aug.</hi> or <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> or <hi>Philaſtrius</hi> mentions, all thoſe diſputes, which diſquiet the World, into this quinteſſence, this ſpirit of faith: and thence as if that Catechiſme in our Liturgy were not long enough to reach from Earth to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, haue caſt into the mint of the Church the droſſe of their owne phanſies, and lead their <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumeni</hi> through all the Romane, and the Belgicke controverſies, as diſquiſition of neceſſary beliefe,<note place="margin">De vit. Conſt. or at. et he warnes them, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> giuing way to the ſaucy liberty of their tongues and pens, againſt all our Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchies, for interdicting ſuch Polemicall diſcourſes in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular aſſemblies (which yet is no more then <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> in <hi>Euſebius</hi> did) with thoſe Mutiners in<note n="c" place="margin">Num. 16.3.14.</note> Numbers, yee put out the eyes of the aſſembly, yee take too much vpon you <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron,</hi> and forſaking the waters of Siloe, that mildly and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally flowe in the radicall Doctrines of our Church, <hi>reioyce</hi> only <hi>in Rezin and Remaliahs ſonne,</hi> which alwaies angle in the troubled waters of Iury, and would faine tranſlate the Throne of Iſrael to Damaſcus from Samaria? Nay haue they not char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her wiſdome with ſloth and Apoſtaſie too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee will not impoſe an abſolute faith vpon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8829:10"/>
the aiery proiections of their diſtempered braines: becauſe themſelues cannot bee believed in as well as God: becauſe ſhe thinkes heaven was made for ſome beſides; becauſe ſhee feares their clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous zeale might at length importune ſuch aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies for the anathematization of <hi>ego currit,</hi> and <hi>tu currit,</hi> like thoſe at the end of Lombard, if a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod ſhould be called for ſuch: but I muſt tell them, that as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>there is but one God;</hi> ſo hee ſaith <hi>there is but one faith too:</hi> and Phyſitians tell vs, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus</hi> adminiſtred as much in a drop, as Galen in a pottle: nor can there be any other way to Heaven, then what hath beene troden from the Apoſtles: <hi>neither circumciſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>nor vncircumciſion, but a new creature,</hi> ſaith the Doctor of the Gentiles: neither Controverſie, nor Schoole-Divinity, but a new life, ſay I. God intends not to lay traps for my ſoule in ſuch nicities as theſe: nor will I make that yoke hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, which himſelfe made eaſie &amp; light. It will not be ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.30.</note> at the laſt aſſiſe, <hi>come ye bleſsed,</hi> for ye haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, for ye haue preacht, for yee haue vnderſtood well: but <hi>I was naked, &amp; ye clothed me, I was hungry and yee fed me, I was ſicke and yee viſited me,</hi> in the Goſpell of S. <hi>Matthew.</hi> I ſhall not bee iudged by my writings,<note place="margin">C. 25.34.</note> but by my workes: deuotion will then turne the ſcale againſt learning; an ounce of goodneſſe out-weighe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a pound of talke. And I muſt tell them againe, if they direct to thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py regions, they haue diſcouered a north-weſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8829:10"/>
thither; a paſſage concealed from the ancient; a paſſage our Sauiour, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> knew not. When S. <hi>Peter</hi> enquires, <hi>Lord what ſhall this man doe?</hi> The Lords reply is only a reproofe, <hi>What is that to thee,</hi> Ioh. 21.22. And when the twelue demaunde, <hi>Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the kingdome to Iſrael?</hi> Hee returnes no reſolution, but a checke: come you may to that kingdome aboue, and yet neuer come to ſuch curioſitie belowe: a ſauing voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age may bee made by the Merchandize of iuory and gold, without fraiting your veſſells thus with Apes and Peacocks: I will not tell you, becauſe <hi>it is not for you to know,</hi> Act. 1.7. but when the young man enquired. <hi>What ſhall</hi> I <hi>doe, that</hi> I <hi>may haue E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life,</hi> when he ſeekes for nothing but this, how plaine then, how gently doth he runne? noe clouds, nor ecclipſe there, but he writes his minde with the light of the Heavens; <hi>if thou wilt enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life keepe the commandements; hee ſaith vnto him, which? Ieſus ſaid vnto him, theſe:</hi> he anſweres to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary queries, to impertinent hee anſweres not: ſpeakes nothing but myſts and ſtormes, when their demaunds are curious; nothing but light &amp; ſmiles, when their demands are requiſite: hee that would not ſhew his diſciples, when they ſhould be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will ſhew this ſtranger how he may bee ſaved <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17.18. And when the Apoſtle is preſt with ſome cobweb divinity, the Holy Ghoſts ſtubble and ſtraw, that fuell for the laſt fire in the firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8829:11"/>
to the Corinthians; the frothy agitations of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet heads, materialls vile in themſelues, coſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the texture, but ſtrawn hats, where the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour may be worth a pound, the ſtuffe not worth a farthing: he only controles their folly: <hi>ô man, who art thou that replieſt against God?</hi> Rom. 9.20. bids them be amazed and wounder, <hi>ô the depth of the wiſdome and knowledge of God:</hi> in the eleaventh of that Epiſtle, at the three and thirtieth verſe! but <hi>when the foundations are deſtroyed, what ſhould the righteous doe</hi> but lighten and thunder? as he doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very very where againſt the <hi>drunkard, the murderer; the fornicator,</hi> and tells them, that whatſoever their pleaſure, or content may be on earth, they can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>no inheritance in Heaven.</hi> God requires more practice then moſt men haue, leſſe knowledge then moſt men brag of. Tis but <hi>a confeſsing with the mouth the Lord Ieſus, and a believing in the heart,</hi> in the tenth of the ſame Epiſtle at the ninth verſe: nay 'tis but a <hi>calling on the name of the Lord,</hi> at the 13. verſe. For his part therefore hee'le not diſtract them with any needleſſe ſpeculations, his intent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to puzle, but to <hi>ſaue them,</hi> in the firſt verſe of that chapter: and <hi>ô that there were ſuch a heart in this people,</hi> ſaith God, that they would endure <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientius ſtulte ſcere,</hi> as S. <hi>Greg.</hi> ſpeakes, this fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preaching, this knowing nothing ſaue Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified, watring themſelues with the ſtreames of <hi>Nile,</hi> without ſearching after the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8829:11"/>
head. For it is vſually ſeene when a man runnes on the diſcovery of ſome newer, ſome neater way then the ordinary rode, he meetes with briars &amp; ditches, and ſo falls ſhort of his journey. Wherefore I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like that Mercury, which directs me the ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the neereſt cut, then the other which leades mee about through Gardens, &amp; Meadowes, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meete with durt in the way, then out of it with violets and roſes. I am content to be ſaved, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire others ſhould be ſo too: and therefore I ſay to my hearers, <hi>turne from your evill waies, for why will ye dye, ô ye houſe of Iſarel?</hi> To my ſelfe, <hi>ô wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that</hi> I <hi>am, who ſhall deliver mee from this body of ſinne?</hi> To Prieſt and People, <hi>come let vs walke,</hi> not let vs diſcourſe in the light of the Lord: to God for all, <hi>turne vs o Lord, ſo ſhall wee bee tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> thou wilt turne vs ſo, that we ſhall neede turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more: or, leaſt we ſhould, when we are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>draw vs too, ſo ſhall we runne after thee;</hi> doe not leade vs, doe not follow our humors; bring vs not that eaſy ſpeculatiue way wee like, (for then we ſhall never come to thee) but draw vs that hard, that nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way, the way of obedience and practice: <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things,</hi> ſaith S. Paul? the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was not, how then am I? Why ſhould my ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance preſume farther then <hi>Aron</hi> did, or thinke to view the face of God, when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw onely his hinder parts; to gaze on this ſunne, when he ſaw nothing but a cloud? <hi>And Moſes drew neere vnto the thicke darkneſse where God was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8829:12"/>3 <hi>Moſes</hi> as an extraordinary Prieſt (for the hereditary ſucceſſion reſided in the poſterity of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>) diſcharged the parts of an agent, and did both carry and recarry betwixt Earth and Heaven: a Maſter of Requeſts he was to God, the peoples pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions were his lading vp an Embaſſadour he was from God, the Lords commands were his carriage downe, as our Saviour prayed on the Mount, and preacht in the villages of Iury.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The approximation therefore, or immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Prieſts acceſſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.16.</note> depends in the firſt place vpon their employment vpwards: they haue his eares before the reſt, becauſe they are the mouthes of the reſt; and deſigned from God to commence the ſuites of the people. For, although <hi>the eyes of the Lord are ouer the righteous,</hi> whatſoeuer thoſe righteous are: <hi>and his cares are open to their prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.14.</note> whereſouer thoſe prayers are made: euery faithfull ſoule in the world, being a Prieſt; euery angle of the world a Temple &amp; an Altar; yet are his eares more open,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 6.20.</note> his eyes more attent to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers here, &amp; a Collect from the Prieſts mouth goes further, then a Liturgie from the peoples: as the bleſſing of any is good, but the bleſſing of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents is better,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.4.</note> and when that Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchizedech</hi> had ſanctified the diet, euery crumme was augmented into a batch; euery fiſh multiplied into a ſhole; nor was the aſſembly fed, but feaſted. His preſence is indeede euery where,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8829:12"/>
but his reſidence eſpecially there, and though his eſſence be diffuſed through <hi>Heauen and Earth</hi> in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy; his glory, in <hi>Exodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 23.24.</note> is peculiar to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; the ladder which <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw,<note place="margin">C. 40.34.</note> that aſcent &amp; deſcent of Angels, that thorough-fare betwixt earth and heauen, was at <hi>Bethel,</hi> the houſe of God;<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> and in Iury, the propitiatory or mercy-ſeate was onely in the Temple: which occaſiond that generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thither, vnder any preſſure or calamity,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.18.</note> men vſing vs, as fruit-trees are vſed by vs, which wee cudgell in the ſunne, and runne to for ſhelter, in a ſtorme: <hi>pray for me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>Pray for me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to the Apoſtles: <hi>Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray ouer him,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iames:</hi> though I may,<note place="margin">C. 5.14.15.</note> and muſt come by my ſelfe, my comming by theſe is more effectuall, as my ſuite is leſſe gratious to my Prince from ordinary hands, then his Secretaries; becauſe the way is by ſuch Mediators, as beſt know how to beſpeake the King, and when.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And, as the approximation or immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Prieſts acceſſe depends, in the firſt place, vpon their employment vpwards, ſo doth it in the ſecond vpon their employment downwards, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their double aſpect, on God and the people. They are his <hi>Stewards:</hi> So S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them in one place,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Stewards</hi> to diſcharge vs of our ſeruice to locke heauen againſt vs; and <hi>Stewards</hi> to admitt vs into ſeruice againe, to vnlocke heauen for vs: <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt ſuch as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8829:13"/>
keepe theſe keyes of heauen,</hi> in the 16 of S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew:</hi> and, what neede I a ſafer conduct, a ſurer warrant then this? they are his <hi>Embaſſadours,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them in a ſecond;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> and with <hi>Moſes</hi> in this ſtory, muſt deliuer man in the Tabernacle, what on <hi>Sina</hi> they receiue from God; and by whom may we expect the Kings minde, if not by the Kings <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsadour?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note> they are his <hi>Counſellours,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them in a third; and, as they are deſigned to <hi>Thrones</hi> hereafter, in the <hi>Euangeliſt;</hi> ſo are they, in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">Math. 19.28. 1. Cor. 6.1.2.</note> to Tribunalls here: They are his <hi>Friends,</hi> ſo our Sauiour calles them in a fourth; <hi>the Lord doth nothing which he reueales not to ſuch,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt;</hi> that is, nothing which concernes them, or others to know: Seruants are ſtrangers to their Lords actions, friends are not: Seruants muſt not interpret their counſells, friends may, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.15. I wiſh from my heart, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>That all the Lords people were Prophets, and that the Lord would powre out his ſpirit vpon them:</hi> But I wiſh, they would forbeare prying into the Arke, with the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thſhemites,</hi> till then:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.19.</note> that all would not preach, which can ſpeake: and, becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls euery family a Church, would not turne euery tables end, into a Pulpit: That the feet in this body would not preſume to ſee, nor the hands to ſpeake: that the clew of predeſtination might not be reel'd vp at the ſpindle, nor the decrees of God vnraualled at the lome: That our Lay-divines would ſee themſelues,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8829:13"/>
as well as the Clergy; leauing with Iehoſaphat, and Valentinian, and Conſtantine, and Martian, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian, the diſputes of religion to the deciſion of the Church: that the people would not preſume be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their bounds, <hi>least the Lord breake forth vpon them,</hi> as he threatens in the former chapter; nor, with <hi>VZZa,</hi> ſuſtaine the Arke with vnlawfull hands, though to the diffidence of their indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſeeme in danger of falling: this is the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron, nor is the whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo holy, as it ſeemes: ye take too much vpon you yee ſonnes of Reuben: wherefore get yee out of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, for ye haue treſpaſſed; neither ſhall it bee for your honour from the Lord,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.18.</p>
            <p>And if any now ſay of Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> as formerly <hi>Edom</hi> did, <hi>downe with it, downe with it, even to the ground;</hi> I muſt pray againſt this Atheiſme, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did, <hi>ariſe ô Lord; into thy reſting place, thou, and the arke of thy ſtrength:</hi> thou haſt ſaid, <hi>this ſhall bee thy reſt for ever,</hi> and, ô Lord, let it ever be ſo. Twas the Sacrilegious zeale of thoſe times, What vſe haue wee of Churchmen now? Who ever wore a Cope for armour, or in a pitcht-field exchanged a head-peece for a Miter? And my reply ſhall be that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Rebells, <hi>ſeemeth it a ſmall thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that the God of Iſrael hath ſeparated theſe from the congregation of Iſrael, to bring them neere to himſelfe, to doe the ſervice of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the congregation to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8829:14"/>
vnto them?</hi> Num. 16.9. there is vſe of theſe, while there are prayers to be heard, or ſinnes to bee pardon'd, or God to be ſerved, or men to be ſaved. Thoſe onely haue no vſe of theſe Liegers, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no correſpondency, or intercourſe with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: fewer victories haue beene won by ſwords then by prayers; and therefore in moſt of Iuries warres, the Arke followed the Campe, the enſigne was attended with the Ephod: <hi>my Father, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Eliah:</hi> Lay-devotions are the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, the foote; but the ſtrength of the battell, the Chariots &amp; the horſe are the oraiſons of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: the land was better ſecured by this man of peace, then thoſe men of warre; nor was it Ioſhuahs hand overcame Amalek,<note place="margin">Nah. 1.15. Am. 5.18.</note> but Moſes prayer: <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>is darkneſse;</hi> all wee ſee of him being evening and night, a perception onely that wee cannot ſee him; and who walkes ſafely in the darke, without the guidance of a light? For how gloomy a midnight is this to thee, that was a <hi>thicke darkneſse</hi> to <hi>Moſes?</hi> the limitation of his acceſſe, and my fourth generall.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The Lord concealed not himſelfe only from Moſes in <hi>thicke darkneſse,</hi> but threatned alſo in lightning and thunder; and although he climb'd the Mount by eſpeciall command; and that to receiue the Law by his appointment, and the <hi>Cabala</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as the Rabbies ſay, to diſpenſe ſuch funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8829:14"/>
truths on earth, which might conveigh them to Heaven being entertained as an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour extraordinary by the joynt-commiſſion of God, and the people, rated him yet out of a <hi rend="sup">a</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt too: <hi>Moſes</hi> being rapt out of himſelfe,<note place="margin">So doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignify the word of the 70, &amp; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Heb. 12.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt.</note> by the aſſault of a ſuddaine, and impetuous winde; for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much hinders the ſight, and apprehenſion as this: The Lord admits him not into his preſence, while he is himſelfe, leaſt hee ſhould fall a longing for his glory, as once he did; nor muſt he diſcourſe with God, while he is <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all this to ſhew, what Cato afterwards ſaid, <hi>rebus divinis magnam ineſse caliginem;</hi> that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>&amp;</hi> counſells of God are not only <hi>a great depth,</hi> as David calls them, but a thicke darkneſſe beſides; deepe and darke too: ſo to the beſt eyes: <hi>his foot-ſteps vnknowne</hi> to the Pſalmiſt, that continually traced them; <hi>his wayes vnſearchable</hi> to S. Paul, that was rapt into the third Heaven, and to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that talkt with God: ſo in one aſpect, and yet not ſo in another: for religion is <hi>meate and milke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12.3</note> ſaith the Apoſtle; and hath proviſion both for <hi>men and babes:</hi> there are <hi>arcana Dei,</hi> ſecret things, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the Lord; and there are <hi>revelata Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.9. Heb. 3.3.5.6.1.2.5. c. 4.17. Epheſ. 2.21.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed things, that belong to vs. Every faithfull ſoule is a <hi>building,</hi> and every true Church a <hi>houſe,</hi> ſaith the holy Ghoſt: Wherefore as in a houſe, ſo in the Church, like the foundation and the pillars, ſome are neceſſary or eſſentiall parts and ſome are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8829:15"/>
like the imagery or ſculpture, vnneceſſary and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall: there enſues no ruine of the pile vpon the abſence of thoſe; no hazard to the ſoule on the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe.<note place="margin">Quid opus eſt vt vel affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentur, vel negentur vel definiantur cum diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quae ſine diſcrimine neſciuntur. <hi>Aug Ench. ad Laur. c. 59. Pſal. 119.105 2. Pet. 1.19.</hi>
               </note> Every man hath eyes for one, but every man hath not eyes for the other; and what an Artizan values at a talent, I may not prize at a Crowne: <hi>thy word is a light vnto my feete</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> and <hi>a light ſhining in a darke place,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Peter;</hi> it diſcovers eſſentiall, radicall truths to my faith; as this doth preſent greater obiects to my ſight, a bed, or a table, a cubbord, or a ſtoole: but it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers not metaphyſicall, accidentall truths, as this ſhewes not the leſſe, a cobweb, an atome, a gnat, or a pin. I vſe a light to ſearch for bookes, or mony; I vſe not a light to ſearch for a haire, or fly. God being to vs in our journey to heaven, as he was to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, in their journey to <hi>Canaan:</hi> where we need di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, a fire; where wee need no direction a cloud; a fire by night, and a cloud by day.</p>
            <p>And as according to that modeſty of the Hebrew prouerbe, the expectation of <hi>Elias</hi> muſt adiourne our longings in acceſſories, or ſuperſtructions; ſo muſt it after ſome circumſtantiall reſpects, in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialls and fundamentalls too: for although we know as much as wee muſt, becauſe it were vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to inuite vs to heauen, without ſhewing the way; wee know not as much as wee may; becauſe God is a voluntary glaſſe, and diſcloſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe no further then he will: ſome he brings by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8829:15"/>
the Peripherie, or bowe; others by the Diameter, or ſtring: as the ſame <hi>Period</hi> was but a few weekes iourney, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> went for the neceſſary proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of bread; many yeeres pilgrimage, when <hi>Iſraell</hi> luſted for the vnneceſſary curioſity of fleſh, being led thus from <hi>Marah</hi> to <hi>Rephidim,</hi> from <hi>Rephidim,</hi> to <hi>Meribah,</hi> from thence to <hi>Taberah,</hi> from the heate &amp; bitterneſſe of one contention to another, till at length, after many diſcontented and wrangling ſteppes, the children grew wiſer by the miſery of their Fathers; and, with the price of their bloud purchaſed the inheritance of <hi>Canaan.</hi> For as euery profeſſion is a miſtery, ſo is religion too;<note place="margin">Rom. 16.25.</note> nor am I commanded to beleiue, what I am able to know: the birth of God is <hi>a myſtery,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> here;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.</note> and the death of God <hi>a mystery,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle there; the Sacrament <hi>a mystery,</hi> in a third place;<note place="margin">C. 4.1. C. 15.51.</note> and the reſurrection <hi>a mystery,</hi> in a fourth; our ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Chriſt <hi>a mystery,</hi> now, &amp; our vnion with Chriſt <hi>a mystery</hi> then; God the Father <hi>a myſtery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.9. C. 5.32.</note> in this place; and God the ſonne <hi>a mystery</hi> in another. And yet I <hi>am the bright morning Starre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.2. C. 4.3.</note> ſaith our Sauiour, which all ſee, but ſuch as are aſleepe: and his comming brought the day with it, in S. <hi>Luke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 1.28.</note> Expoſed to all eyes, but ſuch as are ſhut. <hi>Behold I ſhew you a myſtery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.51.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> A myſtery, and yet ſhewen. <hi>Great is the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of godlineſse, God was manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi> A myſtery, and yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8829:16"/>
too. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is plaine, that they are ſo; but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not, why they are ſo; the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not, how they are ſo; nor the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what they are: myſteries all, in reſpect of the manner; &amp;, yet no myſteries in reſpect of the matter; how they were done, is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; that they were done, is none. For example I beleiue the generation of the Sonne, without the Father; the continuation of a virgin, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of a mother: I beleiue the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from God, which is yet but one eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with God; that he came forth, and yet is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes there: I beleiue two natures in one <hi>hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis;</hi> one, and yet another: I beleiue the Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God created all out of nothing, and that the ſame can reſolue all into nothing againe: I beleiue all receiued beginning from that God which is without beginning; to whom the infinite vaſtneſſe of heauen and earth is but a point; thoſe euerlaſting ſucceſſions of ages but an inſtant; that was not ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, nor ſhall not be to morrow; but yeſterday and to morrow, before the world and after the world eternally I <hi>am.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In aeternum &amp; vltra.</hi> Vulg. Exod. 15.18. a day of eternity, which God enioyes. 2. Pet. 3.18.</note> I beleiue this body ſhall liue, after it is dead, and laugh at <hi>Plato</hi> for defending a reuolution, and yet not ſeeing a reſurrection. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiue, though I barre my dores I locke not my God in: though I cloſe my windowes, I ſhut not my God out. If I ſeeke to loſe him in a Labyrinth by vnchaſt embraces, hee wants no clew to finde mee there: if I flee into the wilderneſſe by a ſolitary ſin,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8829:16"/>
he needes no perſpectiue to diſcouer me here: that he is in my cloſet, when I exchange him for a bribe; and in my bed, when I wiſh him out. That he is as eſſentially in that place, where I provoke him by my drunkenneſſe, as I that am drunke; &amp; the onely reaſon, why my ſurfets beſpatter him not, is not becauſe this wants pollution, but becauſe he wants dimenſion: not becauſe this falls where hee is not, but becauſe it falls, where he is without a body. But how a<note n="b" place="margin">Licet ſcire quod natus ſit non licet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutere quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do natus ſit. <hi>ex Ambroſ. Lomb. ſent. l. 1. d. 9. a. 7.</hi> Pater de ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo genuit illud quod ipſe eſt. <hi>Lomb. Sent. 1. d. 5. a. 4.</hi> Deus pater genuit deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quà non Pater, eſt <hi>d. 4. a. 2. c. d. 19. a. 9.</hi>
               </note> Son without a Father, how a virgin, &amp; yet a mother; how the Creatour of all was borne, or God ſhould die. How the Holy Ghoſt came from the Father, and yet may not be called the Sonne of the Father; how he deſcended thence, and yet is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes there: What the Diuine eſſence is, how it is communicated, the formall cauſe by which one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues from another: <hi>How the Father himſelfe begat that which is himſelfe;</hi> &amp; yet <hi>God the father begat God which is not the Father:</hi> How <hi>the Perſons are the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and yet no Perſon is a part of the Trinity:</hi> How <hi>there is one eſſence of</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Vna eſſentia trium perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, &amp; tres perſonae vnius eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae non Deus triùm perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, vel tres perſonae vnius Dei. d. <hi>34. a. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>three Perſons, &amp; three Perſons of one eſſence; and yet not one God of three Perſons, or three Perſons of one God.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">3. Sent. d. 21. a. 1. d. 22. a. 4.</note> How the Deity was vnited to the fleſh by the mediation of the ſoule: &amp; yet was not divided from the fleſh, by the ſeparation of the ſoul: how all the world together can but make ſome thing of ſome thing, &amp; yet God made all the world of nothing: How this body of mine ſhall firſt be earth, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graſſe; then digeſted by wormes, &amp; then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8829:17"/>
incorporated into man: how I ſhall haue my owne fleſh, &amp; he that eates me, ſhall haue it too at the laſt day. How the Lord can be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; yet not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: How he was not, and yet is eternall, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, and yet ſhall not be. How euery where, and yet without expanſion; of an infinite preſence, without an infinite place. Here I ſay with <hi>Lombard</hi> out of Hilarie,<note place="margin">Lomb. 1. ſent. d. 12. a. 5. D. 32. a. 2.9. d. 33. a. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſi ſenſu non percipiam teneo conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiâ;</hi> I beleiue though I cannot ſee, and there, that they are, <hi>Nimiae profunditatis altitudines, &amp; inſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, ſenſumquè ſuperantes humanum;</hi> beyond my reaſon,<note place="margin">Sent. 4. d. 22. a. 2. Sent. 3. d. 2. a. 2. Sent. 1. d. 4. a. 2. d. 2. a. 1. d. 31. a. 4. D. 19. a. 14. d. 40. a. 3. lib. 4. d. 43. a. 5. Sent. 4. d. 48. a. 5.</note> though not againſt it. Tis enough for mee, <hi>Micas edere ſub menſa domini, &amp; indignum ſoluere corrigiam;</hi> in one place. And I call them <hi>Garrulos ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinatores,</hi> which forfeit thus their intereſt in the tree of life, by this ſinfull affectation of the tree of knowledge, in another, now I tell them, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare others, then my ſelfe; and <hi>Fateor me ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norare,</hi> I know that I know not, anon. Say I <hi>am that</hi> I <hi>am hath ſent me,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes;</hi> or, if thy curioſity deſire more, know tis beyond thy reach, doe not venture thy wings about this flame; as my name is ſecret, ſo is my nature infinite, thou canſt not know, that thou canſt not; for I <hi>am that I am,</hi> no matter to thee, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Credo quia impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertull.</hi> I beleiue it is ſo, becauſe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould bee ſo; and learne by reading to ſpeake more timerouſly, but not more vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly of God. For the <hi>Lutheran Churches</hi> haue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8829:17"/>
better preſerued the honour of the Altar by the generality of their <hi>Con,</hi> then the Romane by the particularity of their <hi>Trans;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kech. ſyſt. Theolog.</note> although ile iuſtify nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and that Syſtematiſt, in his demonſtration of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> by making it ſo eaſy, hath made ſome of his country perchance beleiue there is none: nor is it alike profitable to the Church to deliuer a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionale</hi> in matters of faith, as in matters of fact;<note place="margin">Mat. 7.29.</note> 
               <hi>to teach with authority,</hi> as our Sauiour did, is ſafeſt here; for he that ſpeakes thus, giues commands, but giues no reaſon of his commands, ſayes tis ſo, but ſayes not why. This labour might be ſpared by ſuch as write the truth of religion, it being not the way to Chriſten infidells, out to make infidells of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: for in things of this nature, <hi>Piſcatoribus credo, non dialecticis,</hi> they are the obiect of my faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe incompetible with my reaſon. I was not won by the ſages of <hi>Athens,</hi> but by the refuſe of <hi>Iury,</hi> not convinced by a <hi>Phyloſopher,</hi> but caught by a Fiſher.</p>
            <p>Nor is this for want of light in God, but for want of ſight in vs; and therefore as he is called <hi>the Father of lights</hi> in one Apoſtle; ſo is hee ſay'd to <hi>dwell in that light, which no man can approache vnto</hi> in another. <hi>The darkneſſe is vnder his feete</hi> belowe,<note place="margin">Ia. 1.17. Io. 1.5. 1. Tim. 6.16. 2. Eſd. 4. Io. 6.46.</note> not about his throne aboue; when tis midnight in reſpect of vs, tis no one in reſpect of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while that gloomineſſe is <hi>about him, brightneſſe</hi> at the ſame time <hi>is before him,</hi> Pſal. 18.9.11.12. So that as the Sunne is neuer the leſſe viſible, though my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8829:18"/>
dare not looke on it; for though I cannot, the Eagle can. Or as the earth is naturally moueable, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it neuer moued yet. God laid not the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations thereof that it ſhould not be moueable, <hi>but that it ſhould not moue,</hi> ſayth the Pſalmiſt: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Archimedes</hi> thought he had Art enough to doe it, could he finde a place for his Engine: that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not poſſibility to ſuffer, but he wanted ability to act it. So are theſe myſteries viſible, though not ſeene, comprehenſible though not vnderſtood. The default is not in the obiect, but in the intellect, nor for want of light, but of eyes. For, as it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſound the ſea with my bandſtring, or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the world with an Ell; becauſe whatſoeuer meaſures, muſt bee equall to that which is meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; or, to come neerer, as my eye hath a ſpheare of actiuity, ſees at once, but thus farre, and no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and my eare hath a ſpheare of actiuity, heares ſome founds at once, and no more: and my touch hath a ſpheare of actiuity, feeles ſome obiects now, and no other; and my taſt hath a ſpheare of actiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, can diſtinguiſh this, at this time, and not that: and my ſmell hath a ſpheare of actiuity, receiues but ſingle odours at this inſtant, cannot (with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction) receiue ſeuerall; there being limits defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to euery ſenſe, beyond which they cannot worke: euery one receiuing obiects, and ſpecies, according to the proportion of their nature and condition. In like manner, my vnderſtanding being
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8829:18"/>
of a finite, and determinate capacity, can receiue no imagination or idea but what is finite and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and therefore is of too narrow a ſize, or bore to comprehend the ſecrets, and infinitude of God. <hi>I am the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſayth God;<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 4.2.</note> and <hi>our God is a conſuming fire,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle.<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to know <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the hinder parts of God, in the heauen and earth, the volumes of his creatures; which therefore, at the laſt day, <hi>ſhall bee gathered together as a ſcrowle,</hi> becauſe I ſhall then ſee him as he is, <hi>face to face.</hi> I may enioy the light, while I looke obliquely on the Sunne, and ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become warme, at a competent diſtance from the fire; but if I pry into the myſteries of the Trinity, if I fathome the abyſſe of his judgements, if I thruſt away the hand that covers my eyes, if I deſire to out face the one, or enter into the other, I am inſtantly blinde, or burnt, becauſe it is too vehement an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible for my vnderſtanding: I can ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when I looke on inferiour obiects, where is nothing but darkneſſe, but when I looke on this, where is nothing but light, I ſee nothing: there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a greater luſter in God, then can, without death, be comprehended by man;<note n="r" place="margin">Exod. 33.20.21.</note> as the eye of a needle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits a thread, but is ſplitten with a wyar.</p>
            <p>O the height, and the depth; the maze, and rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of this ineffable God! What Vatican, what Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary of the world hath a key for this lock? This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible infinitude is aboue the pitch of my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8829:19"/>
fleſh, becauſe this incomprehenſible infinitude is my incomprehenſible God; for whatſoever is his, is he: and what reſpect then is great enough for him, that is greater then I can thinke? Or why ſhould I repine to ſeeke God here, whom I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſufficiently finde, or vilify that glory with my tongue, which is too large for my vnderſtanding? their zeale was too impudent that ſaid, <hi>ſhew vs the Father, and it ſufficeth vs;</hi> and therefore I onely ſay, ſhew me but a glimpſe, but a twilight of the Father, and it ſufficeth mee: the leaſt dawning of that viſion is as much as I am capable of, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely enough to bleſſe and raviſh mee; a minute of thee is worth a million of ages in all the Courtſhip, and bravery of the World.</p>
            <p>Againe, thou waſt, ô Lord, <hi>in nubibus,</hi> vnder the Law;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod. 14.24. c. 19.16. c. 33.10. c. 4.33. c. 16.2.13. Num. 4.19.20. c. 9.16. c. 11.25. c. 16.43. Deut. 31.15.</note> and appearedſt oftner in dreames then viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and why ſhould I then dreame of viſions, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell? Where thou intendeſt night, why ſhould I looke for noone? Why ſhould I long to ſee, what the Cherubins ſaw not, which covered their faces, and opened their mouthes at once; were hoodwinkt, while they honoured thee, Eſa. 6.1.2.3. Thou haſt told me by <hi>Arnobius, vt intelligaris, tacendum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 1. p. 28.</note> that the greateſt knowledge of thee is a confeſſion. I cannot know thee: as he commends a beauty more, that ſaith he cannot, then hee that labours to expreſſe it, becauſe this thinkes hee can: and thou haſt told me by S. <hi>Hilarie: non tam veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8829:19"/>
habet quàm praemium ignorare quod credas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Trin. l. 8.</note> 
               <hi>quia maximum ſtipendium fidei eſt, ſperare quae neſcias:</hi> my bodily eyes ſhall hereafter ſee thoſe ioyes, that eye hath not ſeene, becauſe my ſpirituall eyes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thoſe myſteries here, they cannot ſee: and thou haſt told me, by S. <hi>Aug. non negandum eſt, quod apertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt quia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendi non poteſt, quod occultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De bon. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeu: c. 14.</note> know this, corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, though ô Lord God thou know'ſt, I know not how: &amp; thou haſt told mee by S. <hi>Greg. ibi praecipuè fides habet meritum, vbi humana ratio non praebet expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentum,</hi> that the Laver of Regeneration makes me not a Rationall man, but a faithfull for thou art a God as well of the valleyes, as of the hills,<note place="margin">Confidera quod voceris fidelis, non ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionalis: deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que accepto baptiſmo hoc dicimus, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis factus ſum, credo quod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio Aug. Ser. <hi>189.</hi> de temp. <hi>Eſa. 7.9.</hi>
               </note> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainedſt the Sheapheards as kindly as the <hi>Magi,</hi> of the Eaſt: &amp; thou haſt told me this by <hi>Eſaiah, niſi credideritis, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intelligetis:</hi> that I muſt belieue, before I vnderſtand, though I vnderſtand that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not know thee, &amp; thou, haſt told me this by the meaneſt of thy creatures, by the ſpider: I ſee this ſcrew himſelfe vp by a thread which I cannot ſee; &amp; I wonder how ſo many ells of bread, ſo much tiffany ſhould bee pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in ſo little a ſhop, that this miracle of nature ſhould ſpin courtaines for a large window, out of a bottome no bigger then a pins head: and thou haſt told me this by the vileſt of thy creatures, by my ſelfe: 'tis beyond my gueſſe to ſay, how joy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates my heart, how ſorrow contracts it: how pride ſwels, and envy waſts mee; by what way I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8829:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8829:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8829:21"/>
or dreame; how feare ſhould infect my cheekes with paleneſſe, and ſhame ſhould dye them with red: and ſeeing I vnderſtand not what I ſee, how ſhall I thinke to ſee, what I cannot vnderſtand? Thou art, ô God, a center without a circumference, and a line without an extremity, and a breadth without bounds, and a depth without bottome, and an originall which cannot be coppied, and a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which cannot be drawn, and a way which is not known, and a light which is not ſeene. He that ſets me vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a farther diſcovery, may as well adviſe me to ramme the earth into a musket, or empt the ſea into a violl, or weight he fire, or meaſure the winde, or recall a day that's gone as the Angell bad Eſdras; to incloſe the world in my hand, or comprehend the Heavens with my ſpan. It may ſuffice that this God is a light, and becauſe ſo great a light, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of vs not ſeene: that this darkneſſe is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to him, becauſe he vnderſtands, what we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: that he hates not the modeſty of ignorance, but the tympany of knowledge; and, although there be no darkneſſe in him, he may bee in it; the condition of this limitation, and my laſt generall.</p>
            <p n="5">5 God was eſpecially with <hi>Moſes,</hi> here which is eſſentially every where, as my ſoule is diffuſed through every fraction of my body, which yet prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally reſides in my heart: and what an honour was it for the Prieſt to be company for God? That preſence conſecrated this cloud, and this conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8829:21"/>
cauſed that reverentiall diſtance, that ſupple a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of the people: for as the chaire of State, and court is, where is the King; ſo where God is, there is a Propitiatory, and an Altar. Wee are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no more idolatrous by our proſtration to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the table of the Lord, then the Iewes were by theirs towards the Tabernacle of the Lord; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the cloud in the deſert here, or the mercy ſeate in the Temple, becauſe wee doe it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as that Conſtantinopolitane Councell ſpeakes vpon another occaſion, to God, which is there, not to a ſimilitude of God, which is not there; and our faith points at Heaven, while our eyes are fixt on the Altar: nor know I any which applaude that baſe, damnable metaphor, that reſemblance of this to a <hi>dreſſer,</hi> but ſuch as ſtumble in a levell, not becauſe the rode of the Church is vneven,<note place="margin">I. P.</note> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their diſcretion is lame; ſuch as would feigne ſlay their beaſts, and ſet on their crocks againe, in the courts of the Lord, as the Iewes once did; or lay their Saviour in a cratch, by tranſlating his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels into ſtables.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God was <hi>in a cloud and in a ſhowre;</hi> miſts and <hi>thunderings and tempeſts</hi> there were,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.18. c. 19.16.</note> and ſeldome theſe without raine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ever ſince the ſpirit of God moued on thoſe waters, the ſpirit of God hath beene moved by theſe waters. becauſe <hi>the Lord forgives my tranſgreſsions, by blotting them out,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; what my impenitency
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8829:22"/>
hath written being wiped out by my teares: and is then moſt affected with the wounds of my ſoule, when they bleede at my eyes: but Lord, what Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines are wee growne to the ſeverity of elder times? fiue yeeres pennance for conſulting witches; ſeaven yeeres for adultery; ten yeeres for voluntary abortion; twenty yeeres for ſome offences, in the <hi>Ancyrane</hi> counſell,<note place="margin">c. 19.20.23. con. Nic. c. 12.</note> during life for others: and 'tis to be feared, we are out, if they were in; for why ſhould it be thought ſuch a prodigie to ſee man in a dew, when God was ſo often in a cloud?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">c. 19.9.18. Heb. 12.18.</note>3. God <hi>was in a ſhowre, and in a fire:</hi> in a fire, to ſhew he can be enflamed; &amp; in a ſhowre to ſhew this flame may be quenched; in a fire againſt preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in a ſhowre againſt deſpaire: for hee never inflicts a wound, before hee provides a remedy; draws not a ſword, which he rebates not firſt; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes not war, before he profers conditions of peace: and is therefore vſually deciphered in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by his juſtice and his mercy together; nor meane I to divorce thoſe attributes the Holy Ghoſt hath married, by making him all mercy to my ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9. Rom. 15.26.</note> all juſtice to others: every hearer is a <hi>building,</hi> and every teacher is a <hi>builder,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt: and he ſhall meddle with no houſe of mine, that throwes downe my walls becauſe they want point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that cannot repaire,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.3.4.</note> and mend, vnleſſe he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and deſtroy: for I can with <hi>Moſes</hi> endure a rod, though I flee from a Serpent. God was <hi>in a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8829:22"/>
fire and in a darkneſſe;</hi> to ſhew,<note place="margin">c. 19.18. c. 20.18. Heb. 12.18. Dan. 3.49. <hi>Secund.</hi> vulg. ed Io. 10.22.</note> that as there was a fire without heate, ſo there may bee a fire without light: and ſuch is the fire of <hi>that Land of darkneſſe, ignis ſine luce fluvius,</hi> a darkneſſe wherein they ſhall ſee nothing that can comfort; and yet wherein they ſhall ſee any thing that may torment them: God comming here at the giuing of the Law, as he will come againſt the tranſgreſſors of the Law, in flames to puniſh, but no light to refreſh them, ſo that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Bede,</hi> ſo our Saviour ſhewes:<note place="margin">§ <hi>L.</hi> 3. c. 19.</note> 
               <hi>goe yee curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to outer darkneſſe,</hi> Math. 8.12. and yet <hi>goe yee curſed into everlaſting fire</hi> too, in the fiue and twentieth of that Goſpell, at the one and fortieth verſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 God was <hi>in a darkneſse and a thicke darkneſse too:</hi> demaunding thereby what a madneſſe it is, from that omniſcient God, which is in the thickeſt dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to hide in the darke; or preſent this ſinfull fleſh in the arreare of pluſhes, and tiſhues; for impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent man to embroider, and beſpangle himſelfe with the orient brightneſſe of firmament, and ſtarres, whereas that omnipotent God was apparelled with the gloomineſſe of a cloud. Shall the creature arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate more glory then the Creator; or this ſhadow, then that Sunne? Muſt I that am all vileneſſe expoſe the luxury of my pride to the oſtentation of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique view, and my God, that is all glory, hide in a ſhade? Muſt the Lord of light bury himſelfe in darkneſſe? And theſe ſonnes of darkneſſe ſparkle in the light? ſhall earth be ſo high, and Heauen ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8829:23"/>
low? Let me rather be like my God that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of darkneſse, on mount Sina here: and my Saviour, that concealed his glory vnder darkneſse, on mount Olivet there:<note place="margin">Mat. 16.6.</note> the higher I am, the leſſe may my ſhadow be. Let me never confute my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble penitentiall Sermon by my prowd vaineglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Caſſocke, nor attend my Lord, by being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like my God: let my oraiſons be without noiſe in the darke; and my dominion without imperiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the darke: and my goodneſſe without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation in the darke; and my charity without vaineglory, in the darke: and my honour, without bravery, in the darke; and my retinue, without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality in the darke; let this darkneſſe diſguiſe my light here, as it did his; that this darkneſse may raiſe me to light hereafter, as it did him (for <hi>a cloud,</hi> ſaith the Evangeliſt,<note place="margin">Act. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>received him out of their ſight</hi>) let me creepe on earth, that I may clime to Heaven. Whether the Father of Mercies bring vs all, for the merits of his Sonne: to whom with the bleſsed ſpirit, be aſcribed all honour, and prayſe, dominion, and power, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8829:23"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 1.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now that I ſay, that every one of you ſaith, I am of Paul, and I of Apollo, and I of Cephas, and I of Christ.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW little haue the beſt to glory in, which are bad enough to abuſe the chiefeſt bleſſings? or what confidence is it, to purchaſe heauen by our ſelues, which are hardly drawne thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the labours of others; which make the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt meanes of our ſalvation, the greateſt hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from it, &amp; pretend ſuch as exhort vs to peace, for the authors of a ſchiſme? 'Tis the diſeaſe of our times, and it was <hi>Corinths</hi> too, an inveterate malady, and therefore the more incurable. Shee fell aſunder into as many diviſions as her Church had teachers (happy lights in coniunction, but in oppoſition moſt dangerous) wherein euery faction ſailes by a ſeverall card, and is carried by a peculiar
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8829:24"/>
bias.<note place="margin">Praefat. de gubern.</note> This ſide admires <hi>Pauls</hi> plaines, and miſtruſts Apollos ſtructures for the gaudy varniſh, <hi>non leno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinia volumus, ſed remedia,</hi> as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſpeakes; they deſire the cure, nothing to ſweeten their phyſicke: and could wiſh <hi>Apollo</hi> were confined to the deske, <hi>Paul</hi> to the temple. Another magnifies the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eloquence of <hi>Apollo,</hi> ſleighting S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> as too flat and heauy,<note place="margin">Caiet. &amp; Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus thinke theſe intitled C<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. to their faction.</note> nor can any thing charme this evill ſpirit, but the ſpells of Apolloes rhetorique, a third is taken with S. <hi>Peters</hi> keyes, and becauſe hee is called a rocke, ſuppoſeth all the reſt laid their foundation on the Sand: &amp; a fourth likes none, their ſublimated iudgement thinkes meanely of <hi>Paul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he perſecuted Chriſt; and of <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe he denied him, their faith ſhall not ſhipwracke on that rocke, nor their ſoules bee committed to <hi>Cephas</hi> keyes. The cunning diſputes of <hi>Gamaliels</hi> ſcholler ſhall not ſway them, nor the commanding ſtraines of the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> oratour; Chriſt only redeemed, and therefore no reaſon, any elſe ſhould diſpoſe them. May others miſcall themſelues, as they liſt, theſe will bee nothing but chriſtians. Well reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, were yee as charitable as wiſe; did yee loue your brother with your Saviour, did yee not intitle Chriſt to your faction, and hazard your intereſt in the head, by diſioynting your ſelues from the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Tis well ye thinke Chriſt your owne, but ill yee thinke, he belongs to none beſides you: for hee that ſaies, <hi>I am of Chriſt,</hi> divides himſelfe, as well
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8829:24"/>
as he that ſaith, <hi>I am of Paul, and I of Apollo,</hi> in the next verſe of this chapter. This was <hi>Corinths</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, and vntill it bee cured, the Apoſtle can proceede no farther: greater miſteries were to bee imparted, had not theſe diviſions diſabled them to heare. For then the contentious man none ſaies more or vnderſtands leſſe: and contentious they were, their buſineſſe and employment now being little elſe. 'Tis no private jealouſie of his owne, <hi>Chloes family</hi> ſaies ſo, nay themſelues ſay ſo, and therefore he ſaies ſo too. <hi>Now this I ſay, that every one of you ſaith, &amp;c.</hi> My Apoſtle chargeth Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth with a ſchiſme, wherein he diſcovers.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The pretended leaders. <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The parties, ſome <hi>Pauls</hi> diſciples, others <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes:</hi> a third multitude appropriated to <hi>Cephas,</hi> and a fourth to <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The cauſe, this was the iſſue of <hi>contention</hi> v. 11. and contention the ſpawne of the fleſh. Gal. 5.20. for while they are ſo, they are nothing but <hi>carnall:</hi> in the third of this epiſtle, at the fourth verſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or gaine, or pride, or envy overruled their wills, and miſguided them into factions: ſenſuall they are and ſuch are their actions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 I beginne with the pretended leaders of this Schiſme; <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath ever bin the policy of Satan to gild ſchiſmes, and hereſies with the names of ſpecious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8829:25"/>
leaders, intreſſing the learnedeſt and beſt of the Church, in the worſt opinions, and deſperateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; as men doe great perſons in broken titles, that being vnable to beare a triall in themſelues, they might receiue eſteeme, from the credit of their Patrons, this was the cheat which gull'd Corinth: <hi>a Church enriched with the grace and knowledge of Chriſt, ſetled and confirmed in the ſame. v.</hi> 4.5.6. vnlikely to miſcarry, vnleſſe by that fondneſſe and dotage on her Paſtors. Men they were of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary worth, &amp; greateſt eminency in the Church. Paul for his learning, his zeale, the multitude of his ſufferings, his miraculous converſion, his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly rapture, where hee ſaw that hee could not ſpeake. Hee, out of an humble modeſty, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth himſelfe <hi>the least of the Apoſtles,</hi> and yet, beleeue but his owne relation, and you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him the greateſt <hi>Apollo</hi> for his ſanctified rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torique, <hi>eloquent, mighty in the Scriptures:</hi> for his fiery devotion, <hi>fervent in ſpirit:</hi> for his vnwearied induſtry, <hi>he taught the way of the Lord diligently:</hi> for his powerfull diſputations, <hi>he mightily convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Iewes.</hi> Act. 18.24.25.28. <hi>Cephat</hi> deſervedly ſtiled <hi>princeps Apoſtolorum,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Catalog. Script.</note> Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Saint <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> calls him; the primate and chiefe of the Apoſtles: either for the priviledge of his age, or the liberty of his ſpeech, or the honours conferred vpon him by our Saviour, his individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all companion in raiſing the dead, his transfigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8829:25"/>
on the mount, his laſt vigils in the garden; his ſpeeches ever directed to him, as a perſon repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the reſt, his favorite, and darling. So that, if the Divell intitle theſe to a diviſion, hee cannot want proſelites: the groſſeſt errour will paſſe, if their ſeale be on it, for it is impoſſible hypocriſy ſhould lodge with ſo much zeale, or deceipt with ſuch knowledge &amp; illumination. Each man thinkes his owne opinions canonicall, becauſe his ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed leader is ſo, nor can he endanger his faith, while he ſteeres by ſuch a ſtarre: he is firſt perſwaded of the truth of his leader, then of his owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and laſtly his reſpect to this makes him vndervalue the reſt, becauſe hee thinkes none can ſpeake ſo truly, or ſo powerfully, or ſo profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or ſo eloquently as the other. For faction diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders a man as loue doth, where affection is not ruled by iudgement, but iudgement by affection, nor is the perſon lou'd becauſe worthy, but ſeemes worthy becauſe beloued: the eye is iealous of one only, and therefore the man eſteemes none faire beſides. There had then beene danger enough, had the Schiſme beene led by <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas:</hi> but if Chriſt himſelfe be made a party, if the ſonne of God ſeeme a patrone to either, What frozen heart will not thaw at this Sun? What patient cowardiſe can moderate the tongue, or the hand? no marvaile Corinth is divided, 'twere apoſtaſy to be otherwiſe; for how ſhould I forſake Chriſt, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8829:26"/>
not renounce my Saviour? Nor hath this proiect beene confined to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, or to Corinth, but hath gained abetters in all ages: ſome diviſions in the Church laying claime to <hi>Cephas,</hi> others to <hi>Paul,</hi> a third ſort diſperſing their errors vnder <hi>Apolloes</hi> name, all vnder Chriſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
as <hi>Naz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orat. 14. p. 221. Paris 1609.</note> ſpeakes of the <hi>Novatians:</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring their auditors by the fame of their patrons, and venting their ridiculous fanſies as Preſſes doe their pamphlets, vnder the counterfeit name of ſome reverenced author, or by a leafe of title to ſcarce a line of ſenſe. Thus did <hi>Novatus</hi> cover his ambition by the repute of his followers, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd credit to his owne dreames from their piety and learning. He knew his poyſonous errours could not purchaſe admiſſion, while they appeared in their naturall attire, and therefore it was his ſubtlety to preſent them to the world,<note place="margin">Hiſt eccleſ. l. 6. c. 43. graec. ed. Paris? 1544.</note> not as his owne inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but clothed with the names, and patronage of his aſſociates: for, if it be thought to come from thence, an Engliſh blade may ſell as deare, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpaine: he had in his retinue, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, <hi>Maximus</hi> a learned and religious Presbyter: hee had <hi>vrbanus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: one that twice grew into the eſteeme of the Church by a free confeſſion of his faith, and bad faire for martyrdome: hee had <hi>Sidonius,</hi> and <hi>Celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> both of eſpeciall note, but the laſt of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: a man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8829:26"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that fulfilled in his body the paſſions of his Saviour; and to obtaine the mercy of God, ſhewed no mercy on himſelfe: that <hi>wore in his fleſh the markes of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> and might count his yeeres by his martyrdomes. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the ſame author goes on: that ſtrengthned the weakneſse of his fleſh, by the valour of his faith, and endured torments with ſuch ſcornefull patience, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>as if hee had no body at all, or none of his owne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naz. orat. cont. Iul. p. 36. ed. Eton. of the primitiue, martyrs.</note> 
               <hi>Novatus</hi> therefore may diſguiſe the moſt diveliſh proiect vnder ſuch ſeraphicall doctors as thoſe. For 'tis vnlikely God would reforme the will, and leaue the intellect irregular, that hee would looſe their fetters and not open their eyes; that thoſe which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd ſo much for the truth ſhould periſh in an error, or could walke ſo well, without the benefit of light?<note place="margin">The rebells Num. 16.2. the Arrians ſozom. l. 3. c. 18. graec. Par. 1544.</note> it would be eaſy to deduce this truth through eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age of the Church, were it not ſo viſible in our owne. For <hi>Novatus</hi> is yet aliue, and although hee hath no confeſſors in his retinue, profeſſors hee hath many; men of meane parts, and yet of mighty guifts, ſuch as are not <hi>watered by the foote</hi> as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt was, but as Canaan <hi>with a dew from Heaven.</hi> no Schiſmaticall fancy ſhall want a S. <hi>Peter,</hi> or a S. <hi>Iohn</hi> to owne it, nor can you diſſent from this, but you erre from the holy Ghoſt, which ſpake by S. <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Eſaiah.</hi> They hate thoſe Micaiahs of elder times, becauſe they ſpeake <hi>no good of them, but evill,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8829:27"/>
nor can you heare a diſcourſe, but you may know who ownes it, by the rebaptization of <hi>Cyp.</hi> or the Montaniſme of <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Scripture ſhall bee the rule, and only they interpreters: for 'tis not cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, though it hath the ſtampe of the Church, vnleſſe it hath theirs beſides; and ſo become them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that infallible Antichriſt they declaime ſo much againſt, &amp; are, vpon the point, both the old Teſtament, &amp; the new: thus doe they expoſe their fondneſse vnder a counterfeit vaile of the ſpirit, as courſer beauties draw the beholders from their deformities, by the ſumptuous art of their dreſſing, that the face might be loſt by gazing on the cloths: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 14. p. 216.</note> They paint out their ignorance with a tedious cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of abuſed authorities, and cover miſchiefes with religion: the wolfe muſt be concealed vnder a Lambs fleece, and their foule errors perfumed with the Myrrhe, and caſſia of holy writ <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ios ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos medicaminum vocabulis praecolorant:</hi> as <hi>Lirinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>they diſperſe their poyſons vnder the name of medicines,</hi> for who can thinke that a drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt would write conſerues over a box of ratsbane, or roſewater over Mercury? opinions vſually gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing credit, according to the eſteeme of ſuch, as countenance or deliuer them: as a man receiues gold without enquiry from his acquaintance, but hath weights and a touchſtone for a ſtranger, you ſee how the worſt of the Church, haue ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8829:27"/>
themſelues by pretending to the beſt; doe thus, and thou ſhalt encourage truth, yet giue no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to errour.</p>
            <p>Let thy induſtry and care enable thee to giue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and credit thy profeſſion: leaue no doubt vnaſſailed; and, as Iacob, wreſtle with God in thy prayers, that thou maiſt vnderſtand him in his Scriptures. Feare not thoſe ſonnes of <hi>Anak,</hi> thoſe Giganticke writers of elder and later times; nor bee content with learning, which only ſupplies for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: like wilde oates, the fruit whereof ſerues on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the next yeeres ſeeds, falling into the earth, before the corne is brought into the barne: <hi>thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand in the waies, and ſee and aske for the old paths, &amp; walke therein, &amp; yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules:</hi> ſo that as it was once an omen, or ſigne of victory in the * Chronicles when ye heare <hi>a noiſe in the tops of the trees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Paralip. 14.15. 2 Sam. 5.24.</note> goe on with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for God is gone before you: in like manner here, the voice of God muſt be our compaſſe, and the voice of God <hi>in the tops of the trees</hi> too, in the heavenlier, &amp; higher, and purer ages of the Church. Becauſe to ſay I ſay ſo, every heretique ever did; but to ſay the Church ever ſaid ſo, ſo did every true member of the Church. Scripture muſt be the rule, but antiquity the applyer of this rule; Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Law, but antiquity the expoſitor; hee that goes another way, goes out of the way: cite the words of God he may, the word of God he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8829:28"/>
finde mazes he ſhall, truths he ſhall not: there is no reſt to him that followes his owne phanſies in expounding this; there is reſt to thoſe, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the traces of the Church; with the Church there is, againſt the Church there is not Ier. 6.16.</p>
            <p>Againe, let thy life keepe pace with thy induſtry, and ſhew thou enioyneſt not impoſſibilities, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting what thou commandeſt. Doe not proſtitute the Church by thy lewd example, which ſhould be preſented as a pure virgin to Chriſt, thy life being a contradiction of thy doctrine, and the whole weeke a confutation of the Sunday. Tis one of the reaſons <hi>Lactantius</hi> giues,<note place="margin">De ver. ſap. l. 4. c. 24.</note> why Chriſt aſſumed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fleſh; and it may be the reaſon too, why, in the government of his Church, he rather vſed the miniſtery of men then of Angells; that they might perfect their doctrine by their practice, that all might know their precepts were feaſable, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them done, and they intended obedience, ſince they taught it by their owne examples: for who will thinke, that Phyſitian can cure a diſeaſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is alwaies ſicke of the ſame?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, carry thy ſelfe ſo warily, that no ſide may claime thee but thy owne; or, if any ſhall, thou maiſt free thy conſcience, by the blameleſneſſe of thy converſation, thanking God with S. <hi>Paul</hi> at the fourteenth verſe of this chapter, that, although ſome of Corinth pretend thee for their leader, thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8829:28"/>
haſt given them no occaſion. Leaue <hi>Novatus</hi> to the cenſure of the world, with <hi>Vrbanus</hi> and <hi>Celerinus,</hi> as ſoone as thou perceiveſt the Church miſguided by thy example, redeeming with them thy former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, by thy future repentance and carefulneſſe. Doe not enhance the repute of a faction, by ſetting on it the price of thy owne worth, nor encourage a peeviſh Schiſmatique by chriſtning his babe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the croſſe or the Surpleſſe: if they ſay <hi>lo here is Chriſt,</hi> in the plauſible diſputes of one diviſion; or <hi>lo there,</hi> in the zealous phrenſy of another: <hi>behold he is in the ſecret chambers,</hi> in the vncharitable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles of the Puritane; or <hi>behold in the deſert,</hi> in the wilde multitudes of Separatiſts; belieue it not: for <hi>hee is the God of peace;</hi> and, as his garment was, one, and vndivided. Let them honour God with the reſt, or honour him alone without thy prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>marke ſuch as make contentions, and avoide them:</hi> beſeech them, with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that they nouriſh them not; or, if they doe, proteſt againſt them: tell them how heinous they are in themſelues; of what dangerous conſequence; how neere that Church is to ruine; vpon how weake grounds that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth relies, in which every one ſaith, <hi>I am of Paul, and</hi> I <hi>of Apollo, and</hi> I <hi>of Cephas, and</hi> I <hi>of Chriſt:</hi> the parties in this Schiſme, and my ſecond generall.</p>
            <p>The Church of Corinth lately but one,<note place="margin">II.</note> is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied now into ſeverall factions, as formerly the weſt, ſome adhering to his holineſſe at Rome, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8829:29"/>
others to a ſecond <hi>at Avignion.</hi> Iudge of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by the Apoſtles gradation, in the third chapter, at the third verſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: this diſſention about their paſtors hatcht contentions in ſecular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: their contentions ſetled into malice, and their malice is diſſolved againe by a devout and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous envy; this envy makes them impatient one of the other, driuing every ſide vpon a peculiar bottome; they all fight for the truth, and yet one againſt the other. Nor is this diviſion private, but profeſt, and that with a contempt of the adverſe parties, they liue no longer in common, but in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall, <hi>every one ſaith I am of Paul, and I of Apollo, and I of Cephas, and I of Chriſt:</hi> a monſtrous diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per any where, eſpecially at Corinth, <hi>ſanctified ſhee was</hi> v. 2. <hi>confirmed in Chriſt,</hi> v. 6. <hi>called into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of his ſonne,</hi> v. 9. what, ſanctified, and yet prophane? partaker of the holy and the vnholy Ghoſt? in, and againſt Chriſt? together, and aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? in a communion, and a diviſion? you that are thus, to be ſo? yes, for tis the nature of Schiſme to make a diſcontinuation of parts, to cauſe a reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the body of the Church, and therefore the nature of Schiſme is contrary to the nature of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1 As he is the meaſure of perfection, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in vnity; and therefore thoſe creatures which come neareſt to him, are more changed into his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, more ſimple, and one; and on the contrary,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8829:29"/>
then are they at greateſt oppoſition with this eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall vnity, and life, when they become leſſe one, and tend to privation: for this reaſon are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells of a neerer alliance with God, becauſe more ſimple and one, not onely in their particular na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but in the generall agreement of their wills: and man, becauſe of a groſſer compoſition, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting affections, leſſe reſembles God though hee be ſtiled his image; and therefore is of leſſer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The militant Church then is moſt pleaſing to God, when it moſt reſembles the triumphant,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.8.16.</note> when it is perfect as this is perfect; that it is, when it is moſt vnited: for therefore is hee in Scriptures vſually called <hi>peace and loue,</hi> to ſhew that the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to ſet thee at oppoſition with God, is to divide thee from thy brother: this may be ſeene by a ſimilitude; conſider ſome rare piece of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary beauty, how leades it every beholder, while the parts are fitly vnited? How doth it command a generall loue? But mangled by ſome ruder hand, and ſliced into ſeverall pieces, how ſoone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes it the obiect of our ſcorne and pitty? Every part mutually graceth each other, while they are louingly married, and pleaſeth not more by his owne goodneſſe, then what it borroweth. The head is more comely for the ſilky fleece it beares; &amp; the forehead honoured for the maieſty of the brow. The brawny armes are adorned by well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd hands, and the leggs decently joyned to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8829:30"/>
ſuiteable feete: let the <hi>Levites</hi> ſword divorce theſe limbes, and divide the body but into <hi>twelue parts,</hi> which is capable of as many hundreds: and where is the beauty which but now enflamed ſo many <hi>Beniamites,</hi> the common ambition, and quarell of a whole citty? Nor is it otherwiſe in the body my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, and therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> vſually expreſſeth this by the other, as the Levites wife was, ſo is the Church vnited, the faireſt amongſt women: as the Levites wife is, ſo is the Church divided; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part in a Schiſme rents a limbe from this body: this diviſion is more vgly in the Allmighties ſight, then the other is in thine; nor is it vnſeene of thee for want of truth, but of eyes: the body is really mangled, and if thou feeleſt it not, thou art not of it, <hi>hee that dwells in the beauty of holineſſe,</hi> loathes this deformity, he deteſts a Church ſo vnlike him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and Chriſt is departing, though blinde <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timeus</hi> cannot ſee it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As he is the meaſure of goodneſſe, which is as diffuſiue as his preſence, not vertually only, as <hi>Vorſtius</hi> blaſphemes,<note place="margin">Declar. Fran. Lond. 1622. Spec. contr. Belg. Lugd. Bat. 1618. art. 1. prop. 4.</note> but eſſentially every where: and his mercy not confined to the beſt creatures, but extended to the worſt, even his enemies. Tis his precept to vs, <hi>loue your enemies;</hi> and the reaſon followes, <hi>that ye may be the children of your father which is in heauen, Mat.</hi> 5.44.45. For this cauſe hath he made every part of the habitable world acceſſible: the <hi>Scythian</hi> may embrace the tawny
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8829:30"/>
Moores; and Perſia ioyne hands with the weſterne Indian: And hath planted in the heart of man a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall deſire of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſpeakes; <hi>of a more ſociable nature then the Ant or the Bee:</hi> and a reaſon is there giuen by the Philoſopher, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God only enioyes all,</hi> and his deſire is, that wee, by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, might be like him. Wherefore he there op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the man alone to the man perfected:</hi> vnderſtanding by the firſt, him that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from, by the ſecond him that is joyned in a communion. While then thou nurſeſt hatred and envy in thy boſome, thou ſwerueſt from his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compaſſion. While with <hi>Donatus,</hi> thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriateſt him to ſome <hi>Africa</hi> of thine, thou ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt from his diffuſiue goodneſſe, which ſhines eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where: being beſides, injurious to thy ſelfe, and thy neighbour: to thy ſelfe, by refuſing their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; to thy neighbour, by not communicating thy owne. He is perchance a great Linguiſt, &amp; hath erected a <hi>Babel</hi> of languages, and then thou wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt a tongue; or well ſeene in the Fathers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, and then thou wanteſt an eye. He is a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> and then thou wanteſt a hand; or a wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> and then thou wanteſt a braine: pleaſe thy ſelfe therefore as thou wilt, as long as thou wanteſt ſo many limbes, thou art no better then a cripple.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As he is the meaſure of truth, which is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8829:31"/>
to him, and is not his, but hee. An enemy this God is to falſhood, and errour: nor to this only, but even to that which occaſions it, and this is Schiſme, envy, or faction interpoſing, and by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſome diſlike in the perſon, hindring the intellect from aſſenting to the thing. S. <hi>Paul</hi> implies as much, <hi>I heare there are diſſentions amongst you,</hi> and I partly beleeue it, but why ſo credulous, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Apoſtle? <hi>For there muſt be hereſies,</hi> c. 11.18.19. he knew there muſt be hereſies, and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, there might bee Schiſmes. Thoſe vſually making way for theſe, and theſe attending vpon thoſe, and hee aſſumes the ſame in the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: told they are, the fault was theirs, why hee taught them not deeper myſteries: <hi>I have fed you with milke, and not with meate, becauſe yee were not able to beare it, v.</hi> 2. not able becauſe <hi>carnall,</hi> and <hi>carnall</hi> becauſe <hi>contentious</hi> in the third verſe of that chapter. So true is that of S. <hi>Iohn, hee that hateth his brother, walketh in darkneſſe,</hi> in the ſecond of the firſt Epiſtle; a darkneſſe, that occaſions <hi>ſtumbling</hi> v. 10. the diſordred intellectualls ſtumbling on the affections; A darkneſſe, that leads vs in a maze (as willing to runne any ſeverall way from our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, but finding no way) and <hi>a darkneſſe that blindes the eyes,</hi> verſ. 11. a miſt comming betwixt the vnderſtanding, and the obiect which keepes it out of ſight. I would this truth wanted examples, or that the needle in this compaſſe alwaies pointed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8829:31"/>
right: but, Lord, what variations are there, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeverall climats wee paſſe? How doe wee fall off, or gaine the hill, according to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or a leſſer bias? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 14. p. 216.</note> into what contradictions doe our affections engage vs? after a ſeverall ſway of loue or hatred, how doe the pooreſt toyes oppreſse vs? how heauy are motes? And preſently anon, how light are beames? how is the ſame fact compared to <hi>HeZechias</hi> or <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> repaire of the Temple, if this man doth it: to <hi>Ieroboams</hi> golden calues, or <hi>Ahaz</hi> brazen Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, if enterpriſed by another? Thus doth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or neereneſse of our affections occaſion the ſame in the judgement, which the remotenes or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proximation of an obiect doth in the ſenſe: when this is within a convenient proportion, 'tis ſeene in its iuſt magnitude, as it is: when farther of, in a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, as it is not; the diſtance of place deluding our ſight: So are we cheated by our paſſions, and iudge not alike of the ſame, when wee are enemies and friends.</p>
            <p>Nor is this only in oppoſition to God, becauſe contrary to his nature, but becauſe it hinders the progreſse of his Church. The beſt way to choake the corne, being with the enemy in the Goſpell, to ſever it by diſperſing ſuch tares. It hath ever beene the wilineſse of Satan, firſt to divide the Church, and then to aſsault her ſingle, as the laſt of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratij</hi> dealt with the two <hi>Curatij</hi> in the<note n="n" place="margin">Addito ad virtutem dolo vt diſtraheret hoſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſimulat fugam, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> (prout ſequi pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant) adortus exuperat, Flor. <hi>l. 1. c. 3.</hi>
               </note> Romane ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8829:32"/>
becauſe, if the adverſary be oppoſed by ſome, the conqueſt is eaſier againſt a hundred, then againſt a thouſand: and vſually in ſuch diviſions, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enimy is neglected, our tongues and pens being worſe beſtowed at home: S. <hi>Pauls</hi> metaphor well expreſseth as much, <hi>I beſeech you brethren,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that ye be ſet againe,</hi> in the tenth verſe of this chapter; for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies properly to ſet a bone that is out of joynt, reducing the ſame to its naturall place. Factions and Schiſmes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynting the parts of the myſticall body, and as luxation doth in the naturall, diſabling them from other actions, then ſuch as wrong and grieue it. The Apoſtle calles theſe <hi>Corinthians the temple of God;</hi> one, not many: and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> too, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no Church but a Temple; ſhewing what this muſt be, by what the other was, that being built without noiſe, to teach what moſt furthers the edification of this; neither the hammer of one faction, nor the axe and blocke of another, <hi>but the ſpirit of meeknes in the bond of peace:</hi> ſhee is terrible to her oppoſers, but while ſhe is like an army with banners, in the Canticles; if rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d once by Schiſmes, if diſtracted into factions, if the enemy hath ſeized on her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and colours, how ſoone is <hi>the glory departed from Iſrael, and the Arke of God taken?</hi> For you know how ſlowly the building went on, when thoſe poore remaines of the captivity were forced to build with one hand, and defend with the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8829:32"/>And as it hinders the progreſſe of his Church by dividing her forces, ſo by laying a ſcandall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her profeſſors. For either ſuch as are without, are indifferent; and then they are deterd from our communion by our diſſentions. For why ſhould I belieue the direction of either, ſeeing they point ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall waies, the ſureſt courſe to detect a falſhood, being to diſcouer a contradiction in the relators: and if the <hi>peacefull be only the children of God,</hi> what madneſſe is it to ioyne hands with ſuch ſonnes of Belial? Or elſe they are reſolued of a different re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they excuſe a calenture by an ague;<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 13. p. 206.</note> nor are they encouraged ſo much by their owne ſtrengths, as the weakneſſe of their adverſaries: their hands ſeldome ioyning, whoſe hearts are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and ruine being the iſſue of Schiſme. Tis ſo in other bodies <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 12. p. 198.</note> every part of the world ſubſiſting by a peaceable temper, and diſſoluing by the contrary. Nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> the Deity is therefore eternall, becauſe ſubiect to no diviſion; and the ambition of thoſe apoſtate Angels no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner diſtinguiſht them from the reſt, but it excluded them from heauen: as long as the humors in our body are at a faire agreement, choler being propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably allaid with fleame, and the ſprightfull bloud ballaſt with melancholy, the whole is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the harmony of its parts. Straine this to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8829:33"/>
a higher, or ſet it to a lower key; adde more weights to the ſcale; and the foote of the ballance goes vp, the tongue goes downe: <hi>the strong men bow them ſelues, and the grinders ceaſe:</hi> either it is parched by the raging fire of a tormenting fever, or ſhiverd and torne by the violent winde of an inſufferable cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; or miſhapen and rackt by the earthquake of a prodigious convulſion: <hi>and anon the Lord comes in a ſtill voice,</hi> what doſt thou here <hi>Eliah? Set thy houſe in order for thou muſt dye and not liue.</hi> Tis ſo in the Church, for <hi>yea are the body of Chriſt and members in particular,</hi> in the twelfe of this epiſtle, at the 27. verſe. Know therefore that Satan aſſaults not this body, while it is healthy and ſtrong, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 14. p. 218.</note> as long as the parts are neerely compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and condenſated by charity: but like a wily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, takes advantage by ſome dangerous breach, &amp; enters through the disbanded troupes of our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: nor ſtaies this evill here, but aſcends from a neglect of the rochet, to a contempt of the Scepter; and a Schiſme againſt the Church,<note place="margin">Math. 12.25.</note> leads vſually to a diſturbance of the ſtate. Such popular tribunitiall Midianites hauing their ſwords oftner drawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelues, then a publique enemy: becauſe they thinke their ſoules engaged in one quarrell, onely their fortunes in the other: here they fight in Gods cauſe, there in their owne: and he that drawes for religion, ſtrikes with a raſor, the other thruſts with a foile: nor doth the battell ever proceede with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8829:33"/>
greater cruelty, then when 'tis fought by the ſword of the Lord, and of <hi>Gedeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore this may ever ſtand may it never be divided. Let the Prieſts mouth never want a prayer for the ſafety of the King,<note place="margin">This conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made Conſtantine ſo carefull to compoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the Church, as himſelfe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, in his letter to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander and Arrius; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. de vit. Conſtant. fol. 134. See how hee laboured for peace by the concluſion of that Epiſtle. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor the Kings hand a ſword for the defence of the Prieſt. When David ſends an embaſsy, with <hi>peace be to thee, and peace be to thy houſe, and peace be to all that thou haſt;</hi> let no churliſh diſcontented <hi>Nabal</hi> requite him with a ſcorne, <hi>who is David, and who is the ſonne of Ieſſe?</hi> Let the meaneſt enrich the Kingdomes treaſury by a mite, and the reſt weary the receiuers with theſe ſacred iewels devoted to the maintenance of Church and ſtate. Let them conſecrate to the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Tabernacle, vntill the Magiſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand reſtraine them; and before <hi>Moſes</hi> proclaime, let not Iſrael leaue offring. If any vnquiet <hi>Sheba</hi> tempt thee to a Schiſme, ere thou conſenteſt, weigh what it is; thinke how it deformes the Church; how it ſterues the members by hindering their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; how it clouds the vnderſtanding, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the truth: and what likelihood is there, that the Sonne of God will eſpouſe ſuch deformity, that the God of mercy will lodge with envy, or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall truth with errour? Thinke againe how hee deteſts Schiſme by his longing for peace. God the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8829:34"/>
Father will haue but one Altar at Ieruſalem, to ſhew that ſuch as ſacrificed there, muſt be of one minde: and our Saviour ſhewes himſelfe the Sonne of God the Father, it was the Herald of his birth, and the bleſsed antheme of that quire of Angells Luc. 2.14. his baptiſme was a doctrine of this, when the holy Ghoſt deſcended on him in the forme of a Doue, an embleme of mildneſse and peace: his carriage to the Apoſtles taught them to be one, ſpeaking vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to one for the reſt, and ſingling forth <hi>Peter,</hi> when his meſsage concerned the twelue. It was his affectionate prayer for them: <hi>holy Father keepe through thy owne name, thoſe whom thou hast given mee, that they may be one as wee are one,</hi> Ioh. 17.11. but how is the Trinity one?<note place="margin">Orat. 12. pag. 198.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Naz.</hi> explaines it, <hi>as well in reſpect of agreement as eſſence:</hi> it was the legacy he bequeathed them in the fourteenth of S. Iohn. v. 27. his ſalutation after his reſurrection, in the twentieth of that Goſpell, v. 21.26. and S. Pauls in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of moſt his Epiſtles: as if this were the badge of his inſpiration, and none were Canonicall, but ſuch as contained a prayer for peace. Thinke againe that thy goodneſse is ſinfull, if ſowred with this leaven, and thy praiers turned into ſinne: thy ſighs, nor thy teares regarded; thy oraiſons muſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane his temple, nor his Altar be guilty of thy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.23. though thou haſt tired thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cruelty with thy patience and ſealed thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8829:34"/>
with thy bloud: though thou haſt giuen thy body to be burnt as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.3.</note> and each ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath ſhared in thy aſhes: <hi>occidi potes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De ſimpile. praelat.</note> 
               <hi>coronari non potes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyp. die thou maiſt, thou canſt not be crowned,</hi> for thy death is an execution, no Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Thinke againe how he lothes, what hee ſo ſeverely puniſhed; and becauſe it ſuffered a greater vengeance, whether it may not bee a greater ſinne, then Idolatry, or ſacriledge. The greateſt idolatry of Iſraell was rewarded but with the ſword, Exod. 32. and <hi>Achans</hi> ſacriledge but with ſtoning, Ioſ. 7. and yet <hi>mandata eſt terrae fames in populi diviſores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 1. p. 26. ed. Lugd. Bat. 1613. Numb. 16.30.</note> ſaith <hi>Optatus;</hi> the Lord made a new thing, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſpeakes, and the earth, which fed the peacefull, devoured the factious Iſraelites: They went downe quicke into the graue, buried before dead, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo vnworthy to liue, they were hardly permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die. Thinke againe what a ſcandall it is to thoſe without, what a hindrance to thoſe within, how it keepes many from vs, opens the mouthes of many againſt vs, weakens the hands of ſuch as remaine with vs, encourageth ſome to leaue vs, and <hi>woe to the man by whom offences come, Mat.</hi> 11.7. neither the ſtrictneſſe of his faſts, nor the example of his actions, nor the ardor of his prayers, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall labours in the Goſpell, his ſufferings for the ſame, his whole lifes pennance cannot ſatisfy the Church for an houres ſtay in a Schiſme. Thinke againe, that thoſe thou hateſt as enimies to God, are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8829:35"/>
ſtill his children; that all are thy brethren which can ſay our Father: that both point to Heauen; though a ſeverall way: that the difference of many is not in the foundation, but ſome ſubtleties of the Schooles, ſome vnneceſſary ſuperſtructions; nay not ſo much perchance, but a meere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariorum verborum non diſcors ſententia,</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">1. Sent. d. 11. q. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> cenſures the difference betwixt the Eaſterne and the Weſterne Churches, a concent of opinions in contrary tearmes; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſpeakes in <hi>Euſebius,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians de vit. Conſt. 2. fol. 134. ed. citat. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ib. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Fol. 135. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ib.</note> an idle wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and a controverſie in words: or, if of greater danger, though thou onely truly honoureſt God, becauſe thou truly believeſt, the other thinkes hee doth ſo. Tis errour in him, no irreligion; and an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour too, <hi>non odio Dei, ſed affectu,</hi> as<note n="g" place="margin">De Guber. l. 5. p. 162. 163. ed. Actorfii 1611</note> 
               <hi>Salvians</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity pittieth the <hi>Arrians:</hi> hee loues God, though he misbelieues, and erres, leaſt he ſhould diſhonour him. Leaue him not therefore, vntill God hath left him; and this thou canſt not know vntill the day of judgement, the event whereof none knowes beſides the Iudge. While the Church is calme, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet her not; when it is tempeſtuous, awake thy Saviour, that his power may appeaſe thoſe windes which trouble her: As long as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is at peace in her ſelfe, may every hand brandiſh a ſword, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart ſigh out a prayer to maintaine it! may peace be the ſtudy, which in our Liturgy is the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of all! Though factions diſvnite other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8829:35"/>
may this be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Naz.</hi> ſpeakes of his, without the leaſt ſeame of diviſion, as Noahs arke, ſafe in a generall deluge. May that peacefull wiſdome, which S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>is from heaven,</hi> poſſeſſe the breſtplate and the Ephod, no ſeditious <hi>Corah</hi> invade thoſe ſacred ornaments, that ſeckes them only for the Bells, and the Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats, to ſatiate his ambition and avarice. When the Church is divided, and the worſhip of God diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted betwixt Ieruſalem and Bethel; ſell all thou haſt to buy this pearle, with that Merchant in the Goſpell; thou canſt not purchaſe it at too high a rate, nor purſue it with heare enough:<note place="margin">Part. 1.</note> 
               <hi>tanto zelo quaerenda est, vt vix poſsit eſſe ſobria,</hi> as <hi>Gerſon</hi> ſpeakes. Thou art not zealous in the proſecution of peace, while thou art ſober. If ſome violence hath ſevered thee from the body, as plants wreſted from their naturall place, returne with greater violence, and, becauſe vnity hath beene once loſt, preſerue it ſo, that it be loſt no more.<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 14. p. 215.</note> What a ſhame is it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that theeues and murderers ſhould goe more friendly to hell, then Chriſtians doe to Heaven? Let it be the glory of others <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
to divide themſelues from their Saviour, by their diſſenſion from his Church, &amp; to <hi>bely each other in defence of the truth: but vpon David, and vpon his ſeede, and vpon his houſe, and vpon his Throne, and vpon his Church, may there be peace for ever from the Lord: may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8829:36"/>
righteouſneſſe and peace kiſſe each other,</hi> in Church and State, all rowing the ſame, though they looke ſeverall waies. If any had rather be out of Charity with a whole Kingdome, then ſeene in a Cap or a Surpleſſe; may the mildneſſe of one ſide cure the madneſſe of the other; and though the Donatiſt will to Heauen alone, may euery one pitty, and ſay with <hi>Optatus,</hi> that 'tis my brother <hi>Parmenian.</hi> Medle not with ſuch as are given to change; for the Kings rode is the ſureſt way: whereas other ſneak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſages are accuſtomed only to the feete of theeues, and murderers. Beleeue not raſhly, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God, or of man, refined, or debaſed ſtill: Whether thoſe which boaſt ſo much of the ſpirit, haue not continually ſome alloy of the fleſh, wholly or parcell ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Whether they belieue in God, or themſelues; are regenerate fully or carnall: the cauſe of this Schiſme and my laſt generall.</p>
            <p>Schiſmes are ſo farre from God, that they haue nothing of God in them; and if the induction were not beyond an Auditories patience, 'twere eaſy to deriue all, from the concupiſcible or iraſcible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and reſolue them either into ambition, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, or envy, or pride. Leane therefore to none, vntill thou haſt examined their tempers, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what they are, before thou doteſt on what they ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Io. 3.9.</note>1 For perchance firſt <hi>they loue to be honoured before
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8829:36"/>
the people,</hi> as <hi>Diotrephes</hi> did; and like the Phariſes, meaſure their worth by their ſeate of praeeminence, as fooles doe their bodies by their ſhadowes: <hi>rapere malunt quàm expectare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flor. l. 1. c. 7.</note> as the Hiſtorian ſpeakes of the worſt <hi>Tarquinius;</hi> they waite not <hi>the Angells comming to ſtirre the waters,</hi> but prevent it, and with <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. will needs be ſent, though they know not what to ſay. 'Tis not the cleaneſt way they ſeeke but the neereſt, which therefore they maintaine by worſe courſes then they found it, men, ſeldome building well on ſuch bad founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or improuing ill purchaſed honours to the Churches good. And if ambition bee their aime, why may they not vſe this with <hi>Corah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> as a meanes to gaine a Dioceſſe, if not a Prelacy; and make them Superintendents, though not Biſhops: Or if not ſo, to requite the loſſe of that which they were not to haue, with <hi>Aerius</hi> in S. <hi>Aug.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Euſeb.</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Montanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad quod vult. haer. 53. Hiſt. ecleſt. l. 5. c. 16.</note> out of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue ambition to diſturbe the peace of the Church, for miſſing an honour in it, and becauſe he cannot be a Prelate he will be an Arrian.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If not thus, poſſibly they are of a baſer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and deſire not honours for their glory but their gaine: 'Tis <hi>the wedge of Gold</hi> they long for, more then <hi>the Babyloniſh garment,</hi> and ſo they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the golden crowne of the Prieſthood, could wiſh another had the Mitre. If this be their temper, thou maiſt juſtly diſtruſt their Tenents: for what a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8829:37"/>
ſervant will he be to another, that is a ſlaue to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">To. 6. orat. 105. p. 906.</note> as Chryſ. ſpeakes; a captiue to his riches, and a priſoner to what he keepes. there is no temptation more powerfull then this, and therefore 'twas the Divells laſt aſſault: for, if any promiſe can ſeduce our Saviour, 'tis that of the <hi>earths king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and glory:</hi> hee is the ſonne of God indeed, which for ſuch a gaine will not caſt himſelfe, <hi>from the pinnacles of the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Perhaps they are ſicke of an envious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor can their eyes beare any luſtre in another: 'tis not ſo much the opinion they oppoſe, as their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall: and becauſe <hi>Alexander</hi> prevented him in a Biſhopricke,<note place="margin">L. 1. c. 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Arrius cannot ſtifle his envy,</hi> but will ſhew how weak his Lordſhip is by oppoſing his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſ. Append. orat. 18. Paris 1618.</note> venting his fury againſt the Biſhop by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing his innocent truths of abſurdity, and errour; by calumniating his writings, as the <hi>Leopard</hi> ſhews his naturall hatred to man, by rending his image in paper. If ſo, ſuſpend thy judgement, for ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious malignants as theſe, ſquare not their Creede by their conſcience, but their malice.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If none of the former, they may be of a too high ſpirited, and ſtately a temper; and then, hauing poſſeſt the world, with the conceit of their abilities, they afterwards ſtudy to defend, what formerly they delivered,<note place="margin">Ad Quod vult haer. 33.</note> and reade not to maintaine the truth, but their reputation. This was the cauſe of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio's</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8829:37"/>
hereſy, as S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> relates: for, by the heat of perſecution, being driven to a deniall of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, he thought it a diſparagement to confeſſe his fault, and therefore laboured to defend it, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one deniall by another. It had beene a ſtrange ſinne to deny a God, none to deny a man, and therefore this was an argument of <hi>Theodotio's</hi> judgement, no proofe of his Apoſtaſy: hee is wiſe and innocent too, <hi>ſi non Deum negâſſe ſed hominem videretur;</hi> if he deny not the ſonne of God, but the ſonne of Mary. Follow not eaſily men of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for ſuch <hi>Achabs</hi> as theſe, deſire <hi>Micaiah to propheſy good,</hi> though never ſo falſe: nor doe they, when their religion and credit lye in the ſcale, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline ever to what weighs moſt, but what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageth.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly, if free from the reſt, they are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Naz. orat. 26. p. 444.</note> great fiery ſpirits, and then if their heat be joyned with ignorance, their zeale is wildfire, and like mettle in an vnway'd horſe, ſerues only to tire and endanger the rider. Or, if with learning, this makes not their errours leſſe, but more dangerous: for then you ſhall haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Ib. p. 458.</note> charmes of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and curious agitations, though vnuſuall: becauſe they are not ſworne to any mans expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>keepe they muſt that good thing committed to their truſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.14.</note> and the ſame faith may bee preſeru'd in different tearmes; for ſo they meane well, it matters
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8829:38"/>
not what they ſpeake; the trodden way is too eaſy for them; theſe muſt goe where other cannot, and S. <hi>Paules forme of ſound words,</hi> was not preſcribed to the ſtrong,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.13.</note> but the crazy. If the Church haue modeſtly deliuered her ſelfe at large, theſe will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to miſinterpret her meaning by their owne; and force her to ſpeake for their particular phanſies, which ſtudied to expreſſe her ſelfe in generall. Where there is ſuch preſumption on our owne ſtrength, the field is maintained to the laſt man: for like illiterate Advocates, when their arguments are ſpent, theſe Rabſhakehs beginne to raile, and that in the Iewiſh language, to the ſhame and weakning of ſuch, as ſtand on the walls; betaking themſelues <hi>ad argutam malitiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. l. 1. c. 1.</note> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeakes, to the ſaucy liberty of a ſcolding pen; as if they wrote by the Churne or the Diſtaffe;<note place="margin">Polla argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria Luc. vit. ex clariſ. au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. Berſm.</note> or that <hi>Lucans</hi> wife corrected <hi>Lucans</hi> Pharſalia. When thou haſt thus examined their temper, ſuſpect their diſeaſe, and feare their infection: or leaſt thy ſelfe ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne a Schiſme, avoide the occaſions. Thinke god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe the greateſt gaine, and let it be thy ambition to be Orthodoxe: know that the ſafeſt treaſure is in Heaven, and the ſureſt honour: thinke how ſhort thy life is; how neere thy ſun is to the Weſt; and be not ſo childiſh to cry for thy beſt clothes when thou art going to bed. Doe not make thy envy a meanes of thy errour, nor trip thy brothers heeles, when he is running to preferment: for every man
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8829:38"/>
may haue entrance, if one giue way to another; whereas in a throng all ſticke at the doore. If through weakneſſe thou haſt erred, bee willing to retract it; be not alwaies mad, becauſe thou waſt once blinde: allay thy choler with the mildneſſe of the ſpirit, and though thou writeſt and ſpeakeſt for the truth, forbeare thy brother. Leaue that woma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh eloquence to ſuch as haue nothing to defend them but invectiues: for know, there is a murder without bloudſhed; <hi>Iugulaſt is non membra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 2. p. 69.</note> 
               <hi>ſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina,</hi> ſaith <hi>Optatus,</hi> yee ſlay not their bodies but their names; and what credit or ioy is it to outline the deceaſe of their honour, and reputation? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this is not the way to cure a patient, but to diſtemper him; the meanes to calme theſe ſtormes, being for the ſtrong to beare the infirmities of the weake:<note place="margin">Rom. 15.1.</note> So haue I ſeene a leſſer fire (by reaſon of a too violent ſuppreſſion) breake forth into vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable flames; whiles a greater not ſtirred, nor medled with, though it threatned for a while, ere long ſunke into aſhes. If thou art a hearer, long not for meates aboue thy digeſtion: if a teacher, learne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rightly to divide the word, and to ſuit thy diſcourſe to thy auditory. Corinth can informe vs, that, as a diſproportionate diet cauſeth a mutiny in the body; ſo doth it in the Church, the vſuall fruit of ſuch Schoole diſcourſes, in popular auditories, either for thy deficiency in expreſſion, or theirs in apprehenſion, being Schiſme or blaſphemy; as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:8829:39"/>
obſerves in his letter to<note n="*" place="margin">De vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Orat. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The cauſe of moſt ſchiſmes being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arrius</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Naz. orat. 26. p. 416.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, keepe thy ſelfe to thoſe ancient hereditary expreſſions, &amp; remoue not thoſe Landmarkes thy Fathers haue ſet: for what likelyhood is there one man ſhould be wiſer then ſo many thouſands? Thinke meanely of thy owne wit, and miſtruſt even what thou knoweſt: for, how hardly can man wade into thoſe inſcrutable miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which is ignorant of thoſe motions hee every day feeles, which is a ſtranger to himſelfe? if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
be in thy Creede, admit not the change of a letter with <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in<note n="x" place="margin">L. 3. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Sozomene,</hi> this ſtrange attire of faith, or as<note n="y" place="margin">Euſeb. de vit. Conſt. orat. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſtiles it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyiſh idle curioſity,</hi> this patching an old garment with a new piece hath ever beene the cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of hereſy, and ſuch contentious <hi>Ephramites</hi> may ſtill be diſcerned by their liſping Sibboleth. Againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. When the Church hath ſpoken in generall, make her modeſty an example for thine: bee not wiſer then her Canons, nor ſtreighter then her rules. Tis enough for thee to hold the foundation: or, if thou buildeſt thereon, take heede thou prepareſt nor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell for the laſt fire. The Apoſtle aſſures thee, <hi>that, if thou ſhalt confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt, and belieue that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt haue eternall life,</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Naz. orat. 26. p. 446.</note> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Naz. ib. p. 438.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:8829:39"/>
and what wouldeſt thou more then this? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more vniuſt, more dangerous then thy faith, if thou meaſureſt it by the daring ſubtleties of refined witts, by the cleanely conveyance of ſome cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtinctions: though in the <hi>modus</hi> thy owne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſway thee another way, keepe it to thy ſelfe; better an vnneceſsary truth ſhould be loſt, then the vnity of the Church: deliver not a novity, though in the reſervedſt tearmes; for what can wee expect but a Babell, when one vnderſtands not anothers Language? Belieue only what the Lord requires, and his Church: conſider what the reſt, for to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low mans direction is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> phraſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>to walke in a circle, to goe about,</hi> not to goe forward, and in matters of this nature, the ſafeſt way is to be a ſcepticke;<note place="margin">Naz. 16. p. 446.</note> if ſome turbulent zelots <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, through a fiery precipitation run out of themſelues firſt, and then out of the Church: beſeech them, with S. <hi>Paul, that they bee perfectly ioyned together in the ſame minde, and the ſame iudgement, that all ſpeake the ſame things, v.</hi> 10. if thy prayers are ſleighted, coniure them with the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>if there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bowells and mercy, bee like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord, and of one minde,</hi> Philip. 2.1.2. if they yet perſiſt, threaten, and let them know, that <hi>we haue no ſuch cuſtome, neither the Churches of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8829:40"/>
God,</hi> c. 11.16. &amp; if after all this, they reſolue to leaue thee, leaue them not without S. <hi>Paules</hi> Prayer, Rom. 15.5.6. <hi>the God of patience, and conſolation grant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to be like minded one towards another, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt Ieſus; that they may with one minde &amp; one mouth, glorify God, even the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> to whom with the bleſsed Spirit, bee aſcribed all honour &amp; glory, dominion and power, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8829:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
